<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The copie of a letter sent from Paris to the reverend fathers of the Society of Iesus, who liue in England Containing an answere to the calumniations of the Anti-Coton against the same Society in generall, and Fa. Coton in particular.</title>
            <title>Copie of a letter sent from Paris to the reverend fathers of the Society of Jesus, who live in England.</title>
            <author>Owen, Thomas, 1557-1618.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1611</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 163 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 48 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08691</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18999</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S104535</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99840270</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99840270</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4752</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08691)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4752)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 855:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The copie of a letter sent from Paris to the reverend fathers of the Society of Iesus, who liue in England Containing an answere to the calumniations of the Anti-Coton against the same Society in generall, and Fa. Coton in particular.</title>
                  <title>Copie of a letter sent from Paris to the reverend fathers of the Society of Jesus, who live in England.</title>
                  <author>Owen, Thomas, 1557-1618.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[94] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>English College Press] Permissu superiorum,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Saint-Omer :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno M.DC.XI. [1611]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By Thomas Owen.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication and press from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jesuits --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:4752:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4752:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE COPIE OF A LETTER SENT FROM PARIS TO THE REVEREND FATHERS of the Society of IESVS, who liue in England.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>CONTAYNING An Anſwere to the calumniations of the</hi> Anti-Coton <hi>againſt the ſame Society in generall, and Fa.</hi> COTON
<hi>in particuler.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Ioan. 8.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>Veritas liberabit vos.</hi> The truth will deliuer you.</p>
            </q>
            <p>IOHN MORRIS.</p>
            <p>Permiſſu Superiorum. Anno M.DC.XI.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="printer_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:4752:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:4752:2"/>
            <head>THE PRINTER TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>AVING had this Copy imparted vnto me by a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good friend, I would not (gentle Reader) depriue thee of the pleaſure &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, which thou mayſt reap thereby; eſpecially ſince that the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents therof be no other, but ſuch, as are already published in print. For which cauſe alſo I doubt not, but that the Reuerend Fathers, to whom it is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected, will take this my labour in good part: hoping that it will be no leſſe pleaſing to them, then to others. And <pb n="4" facs="tcp:4752:3"/> it may be, that this printed Copy may come ſooner to their handes, then the Letter it ſelfe; at leaſt it will ſaue them ſome labour, which otherwiſe they could not eaſily haue excuſed, for the ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of ſuch, as no doubt would be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous to haue a ſight of this diſcourſe; which as thou wilt ſee by the peruſing therof, is an exact and complete confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the
<hi>Anti-Coton.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that nothing may be wanting, I haue thought good to follow my friends aduiſe, and to tell thee briefly in this my Preface, that the Tranſlator of the <hi>Anti-Coton</hi> into English hath shewed himſelfe no leſſe falſe &amp; foolish, then the French Author thereof. For he will needes take vpon him to adde <hi>Fa. Becanus</hi> to thoſe which the other alledgeth in proofe, that the <hi>Society</hi> teacheth it to be lawfull for particuler men to kill Princes, becauſe he nameth <hi>Fa. Mariana</hi> among the reſt; vvhereas it is manifeſt, that <hi>Fa. Beca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> expreſſely affirmeth in that place, that a Tyrant in reſpect of his gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <pb n="5" facs="tcp:4752:3"/> onely, cannot be flayne by any. And this he affirmeth to be the doctrine of the vvhole Society, yea and of <hi>Fa. Mariana</hi> alſo; though he aftervvard va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieth from the reſt in the explication of ſome particuler poyntes, as thou maiſt ſee in this Letter, which I preſent vnto thee.</p>
            <p>That likewiſe, which the ſame Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlator produceth out of
<hi>Fa. Gregory de Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentia</hi> is no better, ſince that this Father expreſſely affirmeth, that only the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth may reſtrayne and impugne ſuch a Tyrant: vvhich is not to range him as the Tranſlatour ſaith, in the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talogue of common murtherers &amp; theeues whome not onely the Common-wealth it ſelfe, but euery particuler Magiſtrate &amp; officer may apprehend and punish.</p>
            <p>And this shall ſuffice at this time: for I will not enter into that other diſcourſe, vpon vvhat occaſion the Canon of the Councell of
<hi>Conſtance</hi> againſt <hi>Tyrannides</hi> was enacted. Certaine it is,<note place="margin">Art. 15. &amp; 17. Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liff. in fine Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cil. Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant.</note> that <hi>VVickliffe</hi> and <hi>Huſſe</hi> affirmed,
<hi>That there was no au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie <pb n="6" facs="tcp:4752:4"/> in ciuill Lords and Princes, when they were in mortall ſinne:</hi> &amp;, <hi>that the people might at their pleaſure, and according to their iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, correct and punish them, if they did of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend.</hi> But I will detayne thee no longer from the Letter it ſelfe.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:4752:4"/>
            <head>TO THE REVEREND FATHERS OF THE SOCIETY OF IESVS, who liue in England.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>EVEREND and my deareſt Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, I hope you thinke me not ſo vngratefull, as to be vnmindfull of the great charity and kindneſſe, which in diuers occaſions I haue receiued from many, if not from all of you: and therfore am bound not only to honour your Order in generall (which is common to all Catholikes) but alſo to reuerence and gratify your perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s in particuler; as one who deſireth to enter into the nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of your moſt eſpeciall friends &amp; children. Since my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming into theſe parts (which as you know is not long) I haue ſtill byn ſeeking for a fit occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſend vnto you, but partly the difficulty of the times, &amp; much more my want of meanes hath hindred me. Now I meane (God willing) to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come both; and to ſend you ſome notes taken out of a <pb n="8" facs="tcp:4752:5"/> French Booke, written by one of your Fathers in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of them all, and namely of <hi>F. Coton,</hi> who as you know, was lately moſt bitterly inueighed againſt, by a nameleſſe aduerſary in a booke called <hi>Anti-Coto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>;</hi> which as I haue vnderſtood, was alſo tranſlated and publiſhed in
<hi>Engliſh.</hi> I do not ſend you the <hi>French</hi> booke it ſelfe, becauſe I know not, whether all of you vnderſtand that language or no: and beſides I am more then halfe perſwaded, that you ſhall ſee it ſhortly in <hi>Engliſh;</hi> though neither my leiſure be ſo great, nor my
<hi>French</hi> ſo good, as to ſet vpon it. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I write this only by the way of newes; and yet I meane at leaſt to touch all the matters of moſt impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. And to that end haue thought it beſt to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe vnto my ſelfe this method: firſt to treate of that which belongeth to doctrine. Secondly to bring the ſolutions to the perſonall obiections againſt your Fathers in generall. Thirdly to come to Father <hi>Coto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> in particuler. Fourthly to ſay a word of the <hi>Hugonots</hi> doctrine and proceedings. Fifthly to adde certaine obſeruations, which in this booke are propoſed to the <hi>French</hi> Catholikes, and to me ſeeme no leſſe ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for our <hi>Engliſh.</hi> And laſtly to conclude with ſome part of that which this booke containeth in the commendation of the <hi>Society,</hi> togeather with my au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors challeng to the <hi>Hugonots,</hi> &amp; his ſupplication to the Queene Regent, for the clearing of all calumnia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <p>But firſt of all I muſt tell you, that hitherto we can heare no newes of the Author of the <hi>Anti-Coto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>;</hi> and it is generally thought, he will not be ſo good as his word, to manifeſt himſelfe vpon the comming
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:4752:5"/> forth of this anſwere. He is commonly ſuppoſed to be an <hi>Hugonot,</hi> and ſome interpret thoſe 3. letters P.D. C. to ſignify <hi>Paſteur de Charanton,</hi> which is the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of a place nigh to <hi>Paris.</hi> The dedication of that Booke to the Queene Regent was ill taken, though, as my Author well noteth,<note place="margin">pag. 6.</note> it is no new thing for <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiniſts,</hi> to make Catholike Princes ſeeme to fauour their hereſies; for which cauſe <hi>Caluin</hi> himſelfe dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated his Inſtitutions to King <hi>Francis</hi> the firſt, and <hi>Beza</hi> placed the picture of his Maieſties Mother of happy memory, among his renowned perſonages. But how diſpleaſing and diſtaſtfull this Pamphlet was to the Queene Regent, and her whole Counſell may appeare in part, by the puniſhment inflicted vpon one <hi>Antony Ioalin,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag.
310. prior. edit</note> as is to be ſeene in the ſentence of his condemnation; by which he was adiudged to be brought forth <hi>in his ſhirt, and to kneele bareheaded with a rope about his neck, houlding a torch of two pound weight in his hand, and kneeling in this manner to tell &amp; declare with a loud &amp; intelligible voyce, that he had mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly &amp; wickedly caſt about in many places of this Citty</hi> (of Paris) <hi>certaine printed papers and leaues, taken out of a pernicious and maligne booke, intitled the</hi> Anti-coto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <hi>to trouble the quiet of the ſayd Citty, and to raiſe tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mults and ſeditions: and that he ſhould aſke pardon of God, the King &amp; his Magiſtrates. After which the ſayd leaues and papers were to be torne and rent before his face; and he is further prohibited and forbidden to commit the like offence againe, vnder paine of death; and was preſently baniſhed out of the Kingdom of</hi> France <hi>for the ſpace of fiue yeares.</hi> And by this occaſion, there is in the ſame de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree, ſtrait charge and order giuen to all Printers, <pb n="10" facs="tcp:4752:6"/> Bookebinders, and Bookeſellers vnder ſtrict and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uere penalties, not to print, bind, ſell, or receaue any books without due priuiledg and allowance, to the end, that all ſuch <hi>iniurious and ſcandalous</hi> bookes may be ſuppreſſed. The whole condemnation is put downe at large, in the later end of this my Authors Treatiſe: who alſo ſheweth (as we ſhall ſee in part) with what reaſon all this was done: ſince that this Pamphlet conteined more then 300.<note place="margin">Pag. 11. &amp; 13.</note> lyes, about 200. ſlanders, to omit the reſt, which belong either to hereſy, treaſon, or ſacriledge.</p>
            <p>And thus much of the <hi>Anti-Coton</hi> in generall: but becauſe I vnderſtand, that together with it came forth in <hi>Engliſh a Supplication of the Vniuerſity in</hi> Paris, <hi>for the preuenting of the</hi> Ieſuits <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I thinke it not amiſſe to tell you, before I go any further, that all that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe was feigned by ſome
<hi>Hugonot,</hi> or other enemy of your Order. For the whole Vniuerſity hath diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed from it, as appeareth by the decree following which I will ſet downe in <hi>Latin</hi> for your ſelues, and tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſlate it alſo into
<hi>Engliſh,</hi> to ſaue you a labour, if you thinke good to impart it to any other. Thus then it is:
<q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="decree">
                           <div xml:lang="lat" type="version">
                              <head>DECRETVM D. RECTORIS &amp; Dominorum Deputatorum Vniuerſitatis Pariſienſis.</head>
                              <p>CVm aliquos incerti &amp; ignoti Authoris quemdam li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellum, aliquot ab hinc diebus nomine Academiae Pariſienſis euulgaſſe accepiſſemus: Nos Rector Acade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miae ſuper ea re conuocatis Superiorum facultatum Deca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, &amp; Nationum Procuratoribus, ac ſententiam roga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis, <pb n="11" facs="tcp:4752:6"/> praedictum libellum falsò Academiae nomine editum, improbauimus: nec non omnes alios, ſi qui fortè posthac inſcio Rectore, &amp; inconſulta Academia in lucem prode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant. Datum in Congregatione D. Rectoris &amp; DD. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putatorum habita in Collegio Sorbonae Caluico, die <hi>16.</hi> Septembris <hi>Anno 1610.</hi>
                              </p>
                              <closer>
                                 <signed>Signatum Du Val.</signed>
                              </closer>
                           </div>
                           <div xml:lang="eng" type="version">
                              <head>A DECREE OF THE RE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor and Deputies of the Vniuerſity of <hi>Paris.</hi>
                              </head>
                              <p>HAVING vnderſtood that ſome haue publiſhed theſe daies paſt a certaine little Booke of an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certayne and vnknowne Author, vnder the name of the Vniuerſity of <hi>Paris:</hi> We the Rector of the Vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity hauing called togeather the Deanes of the Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or facultyes, and the Procurators of Nations, and asked them their opinion, haue reiected the ſayd lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle booke, falſly ſet forth in the name of the Vniuerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as alſo all others, if any chance to be publiſhed hereafter without the Rectors knowledge, and the Vniuerſityes conſent. Dated in the Congregation of the Rector, and Deputyes held in the Colledg of the
<hi>Sorbone-Calui,</hi> the 16. of <hi>September.</hi> 1610.</p>
                              <closer>
                                 <signed>Signed <hi>Du Val.</hi>
                                 </signed>
                              </closer>
                           </div>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="answer">
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:4752:7"/>
               <head>CONCERNING THE Doctrine of the <hi>Society</hi> impugned by the <hi>Anti-Coton. §. I.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IT were in vaine to relate largely vnto you, what is declared in this booke concerning your doctrine; and therefore it ſhall be ſufficient to touch briefly ſome thinges of more note. Wherefore I find 3. points called in queſtion by <hi>Anti-Coton,</hi> and anſwered or declared by this Father. Firſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the killing of Princes vnder the title of Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants. Secondly about the ſecreſy of Confeſſion. And thirdly of Equiuocation. In all which he proteſteth in general, that the <hi>Society</hi> holdeth no other doctrine, then the whole vniuerſall and Catholike Church maintayneth, and offereth to ſubſcribe to that, which the Vniuerſity of
<hi>Paris,</hi> and all other Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Vniuerſityes ſhall decree and declare, to be true and ſound doctrine. But to deſcend to particularityes, and rehearſe vnto you in a word, what he anſwereth to the obiections of
<hi>Anti-Coton:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">De Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe cap. 15. pag. 29.</note> firſt he ſheweth, that <hi>Fa. Ribadencyra</hi> in no ſort approueth the action of <hi>Iames Clement</hi> who ſlew King <hi>Henry</hi> the 3. of
<hi>France:</hi> but only referreth the permiſſion therof to the iuſt iudgment of God. Secondly he declareth, that <hi>Clarus Bonarſcius</hi> ſpeaketh onely of ſuch Tyrants,<note place="margin">Amphi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theat. lib. 1. c.
12. pag. 31.</note> as are intruders and vſurpers, and no lawfull Princes. Thirdly he proueth manifeſtly, that <hi>Card. Bellarmine</hi> is egregiouſly calumniated by the <hi>Anti-Coton,</hi> ſince
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:4752:7"/> that he affirmeth, <hi>that he neuer read nor heard,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Apolog. cap. 13. pag. 32.</note> 
                  <hi>that Particides and Aſſaſsinats had hope of euerlasting life pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed them, if they endeauour to kill Kinges.</hi> Fourthly he diſcouereth the falſe inference,<note place="margin">Inſtruct. Sacerd. l. 1. c. 13.</note> which
<hi>Anti-Coton</hi> maketh out of <hi>Card. Tolet;</hi> and conuinceth, that the contrary followeth out of his doctrine. For ſince that he teacheth, that an excommunicate perſon looſeth not his iuriſdiction,<note place="margin">pag. 36. &amp; 37.</note> but onely the exerciſe therof (as his wordes ſhew, being truly alledged, which they were not by
<hi>Anti-Coton</hi>) it followeth manifeſtly, that ſuch an one hath the ſame authority and iuriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, which he had before, and therfore cannot be ſlayne for want of it. Fifthly he affirmeth, that it is very fooliſh to inferre, that ſubiects may kill their Princes, though they were abſolued from their alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance, more then any other, to whome they neuer did ſweare any allegiance or fidelity at all.</p>
               <p>The ſixt Author obiected by <hi>Anti-Coton,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mariana.</note> is <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riana</hi> himſelf; whome my Author doth not wholy ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe: but yet ſheweth,<note place="margin">pag. 38.</note> that he deſerueth not ſo much blame, as the Proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts &amp;
<hi>Hugonots</hi> would make me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> belieue; for he ſubmitteth his opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, not only to the Cenſure of the Church, but of any other. He remitteth not the matter to iudgment of any particuler ſubiect or other man, to declare who is a Tyrant, but requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth neceſſarily a publike voyce, and a common iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And wheras many others haue written much more dangerouſly, then
<hi>Mariana,</hi> yet the Proteſtants doe not ſo much as name them; which plainly ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth, that their hatred is not ſo much againſt the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine it ſelfe, as againſt the man; and this in reſpect of his Order; which indeed is one of the chiefeſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries <pb n="14" facs="tcp:4752:8"/> which hereſy hath.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">In apho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſm. v. Clericus pag. 52.</note>In the ſeuenth place commeth <hi>Emanuel S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> who only denieth, that the rebellio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of a clergy man againſt a King is (properly) to be called treaſon, though it be a greater ſin (as my author affirmeth) who alſo noteth, that becauſe the words of this learned Author were obſcure by reaſon of their breuity, they were corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted in the laſt edition.<note place="margin">Lib. 1. de Clericis cap. 18.</note> Eightly <hi>Card. Bellarmine</hi> is brought in againe, but wholy againſt his meaning, ſince that (as my author declareth) he teacheth, that cleargy men are exempt by Gods law only in Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall affaires:<note place="margin">Pag. 53.</note> and that they are bound to obey the temporall Princes directiue lawes, and are exempted from the coactiue, by the Princes themſelues, &amp; by the Popes: though not in all caſes. I omit his car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping at the word <hi>(profane)</hi> which the <hi>Cardinall</hi> vſeth once,<note place="margin">Pag. 185.</note> inſteed of (lay) becauſe the
<hi>emphaſis</hi> and force of his ſpeach &amp; argument did ſo require: as likewiſe, that he affirmeth, that Kingdomes are only humane Inſtitutions, and of the law of nations; by which he onely ſignifieth, that they are not immediatly inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and ordayned by God.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pag. 78.</note>The laſt obiection, which the <hi>Anti-Coton</hi> brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth againſt your doctrine in this firſt point, is taken out of your rules, or rather out of the Epiſtle of Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Father Ignatius, which commonly goeth prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with them; in which he willeth you <hi>to take the commandment of your Superior, as it were the voyce of Christ.</hi> To which my Author anſwereth, that if he had read that which followeth in the ſame place, he ſhould haue found that <hi>S. Paul</hi> gaue the ſame coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaile to all ſecular ſeruants, in theſe wordes: <hi>Seruants <pb n="15" facs="tcp:4752:8"/> be obedient to your Lords, according to the fleſh, with feare and trembling, in the ſimplicity of your hart, as to Chriſt: not ſeruing to the eye, as it were pleaſing men, but as the ſeruants of Chriſt, doing the will of God from the hart, with a good will ſeruing, as to our Lord, and not to men.</hi> And for the other clauſe, which is alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged out of the ſame Epiſtle, where your B. Father exhorteth you, to obey your Superiors without any ſearch or inquiry; my Author reciteth one place out of the ſame Epiſtle, and another out of your Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions, where there is an expreſſe exception made, that you muſt not obey your Superiors in any thing, that is ſinne; though <hi>S. Paul</hi> thought it not neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, to explicate that circumſtance, which is allway neceſſarily to be vnderſtood and ſuppoſed.</p>
               <p>And thus it is plaine, that Princes are in no dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger by this meanes; except any will moue that queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which <hi>Anti-Coton</hi> was not aſhamed to aske: <hi>whether the Ieſuits were bound to obey their Superiors,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pag. 175.</note> 
                  <hi>if they ſhould commaund them to lay violent handes vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the King?</hi> To which my Author anſwereth, that this is an vnciuill demaund, and morally impoſſible, and therefore vnworthy to be propoſed by any honeſt man to ſuch as are religious: and yet he addeth, that though the Superior ſhould commaund this a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand times, he were not to be obeyed, but to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed and denounced to the Magiſtrate. Thus you ſee, how friuolous the obiections of
<hi>Anti-Coton</hi> are in this point.<note place="margin">Inſtruct. Sacerd. p,
87. &amp; ſeq. l. 5. c. 6. n. 16. &amp; 17.</note> But my Author not content to haue an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered them all thus particulerly, alledgeth diuers places out of the authors of the <hi>Society</hi> to ſhew the contrary: as <hi>Card. Tolet,</hi> who teacheth that no man <pb n="16" facs="tcp:4752:9"/> by his owne authority may kill any other, and much loſſe a King,<note place="margin">To. 3. diſp.
5. q. 8. punct. 3. Salm. to. 13. in illa verba <hi>Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis aenima</hi> &amp;c. Leon. Leſſ. l. 2. de iuſt. &amp; iure cap. 9 &amp;c. Inſt. mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral. part. 2. lib. 12. c. 5. De iuſt. commut. tract. 3. diſp. 6. n.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> how wicked ſoeuer he be, yea though his gouernment were altogether tyrannicall. And the ſame is affirmed and proued by <hi>F. Gregory of Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentia, Salmeron,</hi> and
<hi>Leonardus Leſſius:</hi> and finally <hi>F. AZor</hi> goeth further, teaching, that no tyrant, though he be an vſurper, can be ſlayn in this manner: which he doth not only proue by the authority of the Councell of
<hi>Conſtance,</hi> and by reaſon; but alſo alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth <hi>F. Lewes Molina</hi> another of your <hi>Society</hi> for the ſame, and anſwereth to the contrary arguments. And finally this my author bringeth a prohibition of your moſt Reuerend F. <hi>Generall,</hi> for any of the <hi>Society,</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der great penaltyes, to teach, that it is lawfull, <hi>cui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumque perſonae, quocumque praetextu Tyrannidis, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges aut Principes occidere;</hi> for any to kill Kinges or Princes, vnder any pretence of Tyranny. And this ſhall ſuffice for this firſt doctrine.</p>
               <p>Concerning the ſecond, there is not much to be ſayd, for there neither is, not can be any thing obie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted againſt your Fathers about the ſecret of Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, which is not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon to all other Catholike Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors. For which cauſe my Author willeth <hi>Anti-Coton</hi> to informe himſelfe of the opinion of the <hi>Sorbon,</hi> which he alledgeth; and if he findeth it to be diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent from that of <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> and that any Doctor ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the <hi>Sorbon,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">pag. 34.</note> or of any other Vniuerſity haue written otherwiſe, he may boldly condemne him, with all the Ieſuits. Wherfore I will paſſe ouer this poynt, with only reciting the anſwer of <hi>Rauaillac</hi> the Aſſaſſinat to the Commiſſaries, when they told him, that he was ſo much the more miſerable, if he had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken <pb n="17" facs="tcp:4752:9"/> that wicked act in hand without the counſaile or knowledge of any: to which he replyed;<note place="margin">pag. 153.</note> that <hi>the cauſe why he declared not this his pernicious intention to any Prieſt, was, becauſe he was certainly perſwaded, that if he had manifeſted his purpoſe conceiued against the King, it had byn the Prieſts duety to haue ſeaſed vpon his perſon, and to haue deliuered him into the Magiſtrats hands, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are bound to reueale ſuch ſecrets, as co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerne the publike good. And this was the occaſion that he would neuer open it to any, fearing leaſt he should haue byn as ſoone put to death for the will, as for the fact it ſelfe.</hi> Out of which my Authour inferreth, that they prouide very euill for the ſafety of their Princes, who make the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon people belieue, that their Confeſſors muſt reueale their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſions, if they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teine any thing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to treaſon; for by this means they take away one of the greateſt hinderances of ſuch impious de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes. And if we ioyne to this, the earneſt endeauour of thoſe, who wil needs perſwade the people, that the <hi>Ieſuits</hi> and many other Catholike doctors doe hold it lawfull, for euery priuate man to kill his Prince, if he eſteeme him to be a tyrant; it is not eaſy to conceiue what more forcible perſwaſions can be vſed by any to encourage Aſſaſſinats to vndertake ſuch execrable attempts. And thus much ſhall ſuffice for this ſecond point.</p>
               <p>The third of Equiuocatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is diſcuſſed more largely by my Authour: but yet very pithily, &amp; as briefly as the matter would permit: and therfore I ſhal not omit much of his whole diſcourſe. Wherfore firſt he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwereth an obiection made againſt <hi>F. Andreas Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demon-Ioannes Cydonius,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pag. 56. &amp; ſeq.</note> whome the
<hi>Anti-Coton</hi> 
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:4752:10"/> fooliſhly calleth by another name, and affirmeth, that he hath very lately written a booke, wherin he main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayneth ſtifly, that it is lawfull to deceyue the Iudges in iudgment by Equiuocation: which (ſaith my Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour) is moſt falſe. For contrariwiſe he teacheth, that it is neuer lawfull to Equiuocate in iudgment, but that all muſt anſwere according to his intention that aſketh iuridically: and conſequently, that it is neuer lawfull to lye, becauſe a lye is naturally oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to truth, and to God who is the life, and the way, and the truth it ſelfe. And for this cauſe he declareth the manner, how a man may anſwere without offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding God, when he is not bound to anſwere him that exceedeth his authority, and asketh againſt reaſon. Of which they take no great care, who belieue in themſelues, and endeauour to perſwade others, that lying, ſlandering, and all other ſinnes are remitted, before they be committed, and that <hi>the Kingdome of heauen can no more be denied vs, then to</hi> Ieſus <hi>Christ himſelfe: and that for our ſinnes</hi> (ſayth <hi>Iohn Caluin</hi> lib. 4. Inſt. cap. 17. §. 2.) <hi>we can be no more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned then he.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But to diſcouer better the deprauation of this paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of
<hi>Eudemon-Ioannes,</hi> we muſt compare this mans tranſlation accompanied with his lying commenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, with the text it ſelfe. <hi>Eudemon Ioannes</hi> writeth thus: <hi>Cùm quis nullis iustis indicijs in ius vocatur, quia nemo tenetur ſeipſum magistratui prodere, id<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> lex natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rae ſatis docet &amp;c.</hi> this Calumniator tranſlateth: <hi>when any is drawne into queſtion vnder an vniuſt iudgment, becauſe no man is bound to denounce himſelfe to the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrate &amp;c.</hi> which is a manifeſt corruption and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prauation, <pb n="19" facs="tcp:4752:10"/> and cannot be excuſed from malice, if it be not by the latin of <hi>Accurſius,</hi> to which he appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth in another place: for who euer heard, that <hi>nullis iuſtis indicijs,</hi> doth ſignifie, <hi>vnder an vniust iudgment,</hi> inſteed of ſaying,
<hi>without any probable coniectures?</hi> which the Doctors otherwiſe call
<hi>a ſemi-plene proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or halfe entyre.</hi> And from this fine antecedent proceedeth the note and obſeruation, which he dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth out afterward, ſaying: <hi>Heere note, that he ſtiles the iudgment of the Kings of</hi> England <hi>exerciſed against</hi> Engliſh Ieſuits, <hi>an vniust iuriſdiction, as if they were not bound to appeare before them:</hi> for this is familiar with him, to inſert and weaue one lye within ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p>After this he anſwereth another obiection taken out of that famous and learned Canoniſt <hi>Martinus Azpilcueta</hi> commonly called
<hi>Nauar,</hi> becauſe he was of that Countrey: which <hi>Anti-Coton</hi> miſtaking, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth him very fooliſhly <hi>Martinus Nauarrus Aſpilcueta a Spaniard,</hi> placing his Countrey betwixt his Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten-name, &amp; his Syr-name: and beſides addeth, <hi>that he came out of the ſame ſchoole,</hi> wheras he was a gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duate, before the <hi>Society</hi> began. But the chiefeſt folly ioyned with malice appeareth in this; that
<hi>Anti-Coton</hi> chargeth this pious Caſuiſt to haue ſayd, <hi>that it is law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for a man to diſse<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble, that he is a Catholike;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Q. 13. in c. <hi>Humanae aures</hi> 22. q. 5. p. 203. impreſſ. Venet. 1601.</note> which he moſt expreſly denieth in theſe words: <hi>Ex hoc proximo corollario inferri, peccare mortaliter eum qui diſsimulat ſe ore Catholicum, licèt corde confiteatur ſe eſſe talem;</hi> that,
<hi>he ſinneth mortally, who diſſembleth him ſelfe a Catholike in word, though in hart he confeſſeth him ſelfe to be one.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I omit the reſt, and come to the three propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:4752:11"/> in which my Author comprehendeth all that Diuinity teacheth concerning this point. 1. As often as any eyther Regular or Secular is demanded iuridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally, he is bound in conſcience to anſwere ſincerely without ambiguity, and according to the ſenſe of him who demandeth. 2. The vſe of ſuch ambiguityes or equiuocations, before any whoſoeuer, without ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, or euident vtility, is alway a ſinne, as a thing repugnant to humane ſociety. To which <hi>Card. Tolet</hi> addeth, that if any ſweare of his owne accord, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out conſtraynt, he muſt vſe words in the common ſignification, and to do otherwiſe, is a mortall ſinne. 3. When one is aſked by them, who haue no autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to doe it, he is not bound to anſwere according to their intention, when ſome inconuenience would follow, or ſome notable good ſhould be hindered. The lawyers alſo teach that no man is bound to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce himſelfe; and that there is no heed to be taken to him, who will caſt away himſelf, as being againſt the law of nature, which is the firſt of all lawes. The anſwere, which S. <hi>Athanaſius</hi> made to them, who purſued him, cauſing his boate to returne to the Cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, is memorable in this matter: and that of Saint <hi>Francis,</hi> which
<hi>Nauar</hi> mentioneth, is not to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned, whatſoeuer they ſay, who make no great accompt of the doctrine of Equiuocations, becauſe they haue no great ſcruple to lye.</p>
               <p>In confirmation of this doctrine thus explicated,
<hi>Eudemon-Ioannes</hi> alledgeth not only <hi>Syluester</hi> and
<hi>Nauar,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lib. cont. mendac. c. 10. lib.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>2. cont. Fauſt. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nich. c. 34. &amp; ſeq. &amp; lib. 1. in Gen. c. 26. 2. Poſter. q. 69. a. 1. c.
2. Hom. 14. in Marc. &amp; 78. in Matt. ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non. 26. in eumd. &amp; lib. 9. de Trinit. 3. part. q. 10. art. 2. Marc. 13.</note> as this Deceiuer would make men belieue, but <hi>S. Augustine</hi> in 3. places; in the laſt wherof he brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth in proof of a iuſt Equiuocation, the example of <pb n="21" facs="tcp:4752:11"/> 
                  <hi>Abraham,</hi> who called <hi>Sara</hi> his ſiſter, although ſhe were his vvife, which he vvould not haue to be knowne: and the ſame is confirmed by <hi>S. Thomas.</hi> He bringeth alſo <hi>S. Chryſostome, S. Hilary</hi> and <hi>S. Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas,</hi> who expound in this ſenſe the words of our Lord, when he ſayd to his Apoſtles, <hi>that no man knew the day of iudgement, no not the Angels in heauen, nor the Sonne, but the Father.</hi> He alledgeth alſo <hi>S. Gregory,</hi> who obſerueth that this doctrine was taught by God himſelfe, when <hi>Samuel</hi> excuſed himſelf from performing the commandement, which was giuen him to goe and annoynt
<hi>Dauid</hi> King of <hi>Iſraël: How ſhall I goe, for Saul will hear of it, and will kill me? And our Lord ſayd: A calf of the heard ſhalt thou take in thy hand, and ſhalt ſay: I am come to immolate vnto our Lord:</hi> where we ſee, as <hi>S. Gregory</hi> obſerueth, that God appoynted him to couer, and hide his deſigne with words and actions different from the intention, with which <hi>Saul</hi> would demaund him.</p>
               <p>To theſe might be added diuers examples which my author produceth of <hi>Iacob, Dauid, Raphael,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 27.24. 1. Reg. 21.13. Tob. 5.15. Luc. 2.46. Mat. 24.36. Io. 2.19. Luc. 24.28.</note> and our Sauiour himſelfe not once but often. But I will not weary you with needleſſe repetitions of ſuch thinges, as you know already. VVherefore I will conclude this whole paragraph, only noting what is anſwered to
<hi>Anti-Coton,</hi> who chargeth <hi>Eudemon-Ioannes</hi> and <hi>Sylueſter, that by iudgment, which is not true, but vſurped vpon thoſe who are not ſubiects, they meane the iudgement of ciuill Magiſtrates vpon Clergy men, and principally vpon</hi> Ieſuites, <hi>who are not ſubiect ſo much as to Biſhops.</hi> To this my Author anſwereth; that theſe wordes conteyne a double colluſion. For <pb n="22" facs="tcp:4752:12"/> both <hi>Ieſuits</hi> are ſubiect to Biſhops in the ſame manner, that all other Religious men are; and Clergy-men whether they be regular or ſecular, are ſubiect to all di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectiue lawes, &amp; to the coactiue alſo in certaine enor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous caſes, which are called <hi>(priuiledged)</hi> of which ſort are all treaſons, and conſequently they are ſubiect alſo to the Magiſtrates, who haue the adminiſtration and execution of them. And to this effect my Author anſwering to the eight dema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of <hi>Anti-Coton,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pag.
176.</note> which was: Whether a <hi>Ieſuite</hi> being accuſed of treaſon, and kept priſoner therupon, may lawfully vſe Equiuoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in his anſwere? ſayth, that hitherto no <hi>Ieſuite</hi> hath byn truly accuſed of any ſuch crime, nor by Gods aſſiſtance ſhall euer be hereafter. But if ſuch a caſe ſhould happen, neyther he, nor any other could lawfully vſe Equiuocation, anſwering thoſe, who ſhould demand them iuridically.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>THE SOLVTIONS TO the perſonall obiections againſt the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the Society. <hi>§. II.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>MY meaning is in this Paragraph, briefly to collect all obiections againſt the <hi>Society,</hi> whether they be generall or particuler, only excepting thoſe againſt <hi>F. Coton,</hi> which are ſo many as that they may better be produced ſeuerally by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues. Only I thinke it needleſſe to ſay any thing concerning <hi>Engliſh</hi> affaires, ſo well knowne to you, &amp; wherin it ſeemeth the writer of this hath not had ſo <pb n="23" facs="tcp:4752:12"/> full information as might haue beene wiſhed; and I would not alſo willingly inſert any thing, which might offend his Maieſtie or the State, eſpecially becauſe I know, that this is your deſire alſo: and no doubt you haue ſeene <hi>F. Eudemon-Ioannes</hi> his booke, which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teineth much more, then I can relate out of this. Wherefore omitting this I will relate the reſt, in the ſame order that I find the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> recited, becauſe my leaſure will not permit me to put them into any other method. I will alſo chiefly inſiſt vpon thoſe, as were fathered by
<hi>Anti-Coton</hi> vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> particuler authors, for the other being affirmed without proof, need no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther anſwere but a bare deniall; eſpecially ſince we ſee, that this ſilence could not proceed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> want of will, or fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reſpect to any, ſince that in theſe other calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niations the greateſt perſonages in <hi>France</hi> are named.</p>
               <p>Firſt then my Author affirmeth,<note place="margin">Pag.
39.</note> that the heretikes of <hi>France</hi> giue out, that
<hi>Mariana</hi> induced <hi>Rauaillac</hi> to giue that vnfortunate, and execrable blow, and that he knew the booke all by hart. To which he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyeth, and will reply an hundreth and an hundreth tymes, vnder payn of looſing both honour and life that <hi>Rauaillac</hi> did neuer ſee, read, nor hear the name of <hi>Mariana,</hi> if it were not, when he was demaunded whether he had read him or not, &amp; he anſwered, no: and that he knew not who he was, witneſſe the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerend Fa. <hi>M. Coeffeteau:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Coeffeteau</note> witneſſe alſo the verball proceſſe it ſelfe; yea my author addeth, that though <hi>Rauaillac</hi> had read this book, yet it is moſt falſe, that <hi>Mariana</hi> teacheth the murther, which this vnfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate parricide committed: yea in ſome ſort it might haue bin wiſhed, that <hi>Rauaillac</hi> had read <hi>Mariana;</hi> if
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:4752:13"/> he could haue vnderſtood him: for <hi>Mariana</hi> teacheth manifeſtly and expreſſely (as F. <hi>Gretzerus</hi> ſheweth) that a lawfull Prince cannot be ſlain by any particuler man, by his priuate authority, ſaying nothing in that poynt otherwiſe then the Councell of
<hi>Conſtance,</hi> and the Decrees of <hi>Sorbon.</hi> But his error was afterward, when he determined the publike iudgment to the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation of the learned, although in this alſo he hath limited his opinion to the caſe of neceſſity, and to the comon voyce, and vnder this condition, that the ſaid publik iudgment cannot be had by other means. In which fearing notwithſtanding, and perceyuing in ſome ſort, that he was gone too farre, he ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth himſelfe not only to the cenſure of the Church, but alſo to the iudgment of any other.</p>
               <p>Moreouer there can be no other reaſon giuen, why no ſoueraigne Prince hath taken exception againſt him hitherto, but becauſe he ſpeaketh onely of Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants, in the number of which they eſteeme not them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to be. And the Inquiſition of <hi>Spaine,</hi> which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe is very rigorous, &amp; the Pope himſelfe, who as a temporall Prince ſhould be as much intereſſed as others, haue not hitherto thought, that he deſerued any further cenſure. Finally my Author noteth, how falſly and maliciouſly <hi>Anti-Coton</hi> ſlandereth <hi>Mariana,</hi> making him to meane by the iudiciall ſentence, the depoſition made by the Pope; and by the approbation of learned men, the counſaile of the
<hi>Ieſuits:</hi> of whome <hi>Mariana</hi> maketh no mention; and neyther the Pope, nor the <hi>Ieſuites</hi> are once named through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out thoſe two Chapters, which treat of this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:4752:13"/>The next obiection of <hi>Anti-Coton</hi> is not worth the reciting, for your Reuerend F. Generall and the Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour alſo, who gaue leaue that the booke of <hi>F. Maria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi> ſhould be printed, cannot be blamed at all, ſince that F. Generall committed the matter to the Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours and Prouincials, as he vſeth in ſuch occaſions: and he had no reaſon to vſe any particuler diligence concerning this booke, before he had notice therof: which as he teſtifieth by his letter to the Prouinciall Congregation of <hi>France,</hi> was only after the booke was printed and publiſhed, at which time he gaue order preſently for the correcting and ſuppreſſing therof. And this ſeemeth one chiefe cauſe, why it was neuer reprinted by any Catholike, and had bene long ſince extinguiſhed, had not ſome Proteſtants beene more diligent and buſy, then they needed. The Viſitour alſo was not to examine the booke in particuler, but to commit it to three learned men, who partly by the authority and learning of <hi>F. Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ana,</hi> and partly by the limitations and moderations which he vſeth, might be induced to giue their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent; but to theſe three, my authour oppoſeth 30. or 40. who allowed the 13. or 14. books of the <hi>Society,</hi> wherein the contrary doctrine is taught.</p>
               <p>The next calumniation againſt your Fathers is,<note place="margin">Pag. 42.</note> that they reigne in <hi>Rome.</hi> To which my Author an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwereth, that this lying ſlaunder is iniurious to the Cardinals, and his Holyneſſe himſelfe, whome to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the <hi>Ieſuits</hi> he would make odious to all Eccleſiaſticall perſons. And beſides euery man kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth, that the M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. of the ſacred Palace, to whome the cenſure of books belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geth, is of <hi>S. Dominicks</hi> Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. <pb n="26" facs="tcp:4752:14"/> To this we may ioyne another, which followeth a little after; that your Fathers in
<hi>France</hi> are in publik hatred or diſgrace;<note place="margin">Pag.
44.</note> which my Author affirmeth to be falſe, if by publike hatred he vnderſtand not the cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable affection, which the <hi>Hugonots</hi> beare them, who (if they were hated by others ſo much) ſhould not need to take ſo great paines, to inuent and publiſh ſlanderous libels againſt them, without intermiſſion, <hi>velut agmine facto.</hi> But the truth is that both King and Queene do honour them with particuler affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, togeather with all the Princes and Great men of the Court, as alſo the reſt of the Nobility, and three parts of the whole Sate, beſides 30. thouſand Schollers whoſe parents cannot be fewer.</p>
               <p>But let vs heare more. <hi>There are aliue at this day</hi> (ſaith Anti-Coton) <hi>in</hi> Paris <hi>aboue</hi> 2.<note place="margin">Pag.
48.</note> 
                  <hi>thouſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d witneſſes, who will teſtify, that Iames Clement ordinarily freque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted the</hi> Ieſuits, <hi>and that ſome of them accompanied him euen to the towne ditch, when he went out of</hi> Paris <hi>to giue the blow:</hi> But my Author anſwereth the improbability &amp; abſurdity of this calumniation; becauſe there was no ſenſe, that the
<hi>Ieſuits</hi> ſhould ſhew themſelues in that manner, as well for their owne ſafety, as not to bring the other into queſtion. Secondly the Court of Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament may ſeeme to haue byn very negligent, if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong 2. thouſand witneſſes, they could not get one to diſcouer the complices. Thirdly this calumniator himſelfe may iuſtly be called in queſtion, why he did not bring forth theſe witneſſes ſooner. That which followeth of Pope <hi>Sixtus</hi> 5. his ſpeach, and concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>Guignard,</hi> is affirmed without proofe, and ſome things of moſt importance are plaine falſifications, <pb n="27" facs="tcp:4752:14"/> and grounded only vpon flying and vulgar reports, as would appeare, if the proceſſe it ſelfe might be ſeene. Of which ſort that alſo ſeemeth to be of his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing placed among the martyrs of the <hi>Society,</hi> ſince that (as my Author teſtifieth) he is not ſo much as in thoſe catalogues which were printed at <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wherefore theſe and ſuch other fraudulent &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious inuentions are ſufficiently confuted by that, which is certayn; that the Fathers of the <hi>Society</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake father and mother, leauing their riches, and hopes of preferment, go to the <hi>Indies</hi> and new found land; are vſed and loued by the greateſt Princes of the world, honoured in
<hi>Italy, France, Spayne, Polo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia, Germany, Aethiopia, Iaponia, China;</hi> where they haue very many Colledges, and are exceedingly deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in all places, being eſteemed one of the chiefeſt vpholders of the faith, ſent by Gods prouidence in the ſame time that <hi>Luther</hi> and <hi>Caluin</hi> apoſtated; and therefore no meruaile, though they be ſo hated by Hereticks, and perſecuted by all Schiſmatikes. I ſhal not need to tell the Reader, how falſly the booke inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled <hi>De iuſta abdicatione Henrici</hi> 3. is inſinuated to be written by a <hi>Ieſuit;</hi> ſince that it is manifeſt, that they had nothing to do with it, no more then with that other of <hi>Franciſcus Verona Conſtantinus,</hi> who wrote the Apology for
<hi>Iohn Chaſtell.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anti-Coton</hi> writeth pag. 28. that F. <hi>Fronton du Duc,</hi> had affirmed to <hi>Monſieur Cazaubon,</hi> that,<note place="margin">Pag. 72.</note> 
                  <hi>it were better that all Kinges ſhould be ſlayn, then that one Confeſsion ſhould be reuealed.</hi> All which notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding is conuinced of falſity by a letter written by
<hi>Monſieur Cazaubon</hi> himſelfe to the ſame Father in
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:4752:15"/> theſe wordes: <hi>Quod ſcribis de</hi> Anti-Cotono,
<hi>ego ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rò palàm dixi apud multos, auctorem libri, quiſquis ille ſit, parùm ſibi, cùm illa ſcriberet, cauiſſe, quòd me non adierit: ſi feciſſet, numquam dixiſſet ea te mihi dixiſſe, quae profecto non dixiſti.</hi> Concerning that, which you write of <hi>Anti-Coton,</hi> I haue openly ſayd before many, that the Author of that booke, whoſoeuer he be, prouided not well for himſelfe, when he wrote ſo, in not repayring to me: which if he had done, he would neuer haue ſayd, that you ſayd thoſe thinges to me, which certeynly you ſayd not.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pag. 106.</note>I will not omit that friuolous obiection, that <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the</hi> Society <hi>was in the world, no man had euer heard, that the liues of Kings were aſſaulted vnder the ſhadow of Religion;</hi> which my Author deſeruedly calleth an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragious and iniurious lye, ioyned with a manifeſt contradiction; for if he ſpeake abſolutly of violent death, can he be ignorant, that the <hi>Caeſars, Neroes, Domitians</hi> dyed ſuch? Hath he neuer read the hiſtory of that Countrey, in which they be recited (an horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, deteſtable, and lamentable thing) by dozens? Did not the Satyricall Poet write long ſince, as the meaneſt ſchollers know,
<q>
                     <l>Ad generum Cereris ſine caede &amp; ſanguine pauci</l>
                     <l>Deſcendunt Reges, &amp; ſicca morte Tyranni?</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>And if he vnderſtandeth it of the pretext of religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and conſcience, is not this a cloke, that is now worne out, hauing bin vſed ſo much? Is not this the pretext, vnder which all factious and rebellious ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits haue euer couered their reuolutions, rebellions and murthers? Is not this alſo to contradict himſelfe, hauing in the beginning of his Libell told vs, that <pb n="29" facs="tcp:4752:15"/> 
                  <hi>Lewes</hi> Duke of <hi>Orleans</hi> brother to King <hi>Charles</hi> the 6. was ſlayn by <hi>Iohn</hi> Duke of
<hi>Burgundy,</hi> and this mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther defended by <hi>Iohn Petit</hi> vnder the colour of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience?</p>
               <p>But let him vnderſtand it as he will (ſaith my Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor) we returne it vpon him, &amp; ſay truly, that before <hi>Caluin</hi> preached at
<hi>Geneua</hi> and others of his ſect at <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chell, Nimes,</hi> and
<hi>Mont-auban,</hi> no man had heard tell eyther of the conſpiracy of
<hi>Amboyſe</hi> for the treaſon of <hi>Meaux;</hi> nor the ſurpriſing of <hi>Orleans, Bourges, Lyons</hi> and of ſo many other Cittyes: nor of the battels of <hi>Moncontour, Iarnac,</hi> &amp; <hi>S. Denis,</hi> or of ſo many Lance-knights &amp; Reyſtres called into <hi>France</hi> againſt
<hi>France;</hi> &amp; this againſt the State, vnder the ſhadow of religion, &amp; by thoſe, who cal themſelues the Reformers of the world. Wheras the <hi>Society</hi> is no more cauſe of that, which is obiected, then the other Religious Orders, which came into <hi>France</hi> a little before, or in the ſame time, or a little after it. We may likewiſe ſay, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Apoſtles bega<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to follow our Sauiour, ther was no ſpeach of the treaſon of <hi>Iudas,</hi> &amp; yet it followeth not from hence, that <hi>S. Peter</hi> &amp; <hi>S. Iohn</hi> are to be bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med. Muſt the concurrence of times communicate all the ſinnes which are committed, to al that are then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liue? If this reaſon were of force, we ſhould by the ſame, attribute to the Fathers the perfection of al me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanical arts, &amp; warlike exployts, of Policy, Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy &amp; Diuinity &amp;c. which haue flouriſhed ſince the <hi>Society</hi> bega<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. As therfore this would be a great preſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption in them to attribute theſe things vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues ſo likewiſe it is an intolerable malice in others to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thoſe infamous atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pts. I wil not go for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward <pb n="30" facs="tcp:4752:16"/> (as my Author doth) to confute this fellowes fooleries, who compareth <hi>France</hi> to the temple of
<hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donis,</hi> the <hi>Ieſuites</hi> to Lyons and Tygers, and
<hi>Spaine</hi> to a deſert or wilderneſſe, out of which they ſhould come.</p>
               <p>Wherfore omitting this, and comming to his par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular obiections, my Author ſheweth at large out of <hi>Fa. Richeome,</hi> how vnprobable it is, that any of the <hi>Society</hi> were of <hi>Chaſtels</hi> Councel, ſince than no force of torment could euer bring that yong man to confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe any ſuch matter, which no doubt God would haue brought to light, how obſtinate ſoeuer the offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der had bin, if they had bin faulty.
<hi>Anti-Coton</hi> alſo falſifieth the Regiſters of the Court, making them to affirme, that <hi>Chastell</hi> had ſtudied Diuinity vnder <hi>F. Gueret;</hi> wheras that Father at that time had not heard one yeare of Diuinity himſelfe. He affirmeth likewiſe out of the ſame, that
<hi>Chaſtell</hi> had confeſſed his being in a chamber of meditations, painted round about with diuels; wheras there was neuer any ſuch chamber at all, as they can teſtify who viſited the Colledge, and among an hundreth thouſand Schollers which the <hi>Society</hi> hath had in <hi>France,</hi> no one can be produced, that euer did ſee any ſuch Chamber. And what can be more deſired to ſhew the innocency of the <hi>Society,</hi> then that
<hi>F. Gueret</hi> himſelfe, who was thought moſt guilty, was ſent back being cleared by the Court, after both ordinarie and extraordinarie examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons?</p>
               <p>As for their expulſion, which notwithſtanding enſued heerupon, and the <hi>Pyramis</hi> which was ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to their diſgrace, my Author ſayth, that he will <pb n="31" facs="tcp:4752:16"/> not ſay with ſome, that it proceeded from the ſway of the time: nor with others,
<q>
                     <l>Pyramidem Rex ſtare vetat, ne quaerito cauſam,</l>
                     <l>Indicta cauſa pulſus &amp; ordo fuit:</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>But he will only ſay, that he had rather yeeld to the iudgment of the Court, then cenſure it: and that there cannot too much rigour be vſed, to make the crime of treaſon deteſtable. And he addeth, that the King himſelfe had a different iudgment from this Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumniator, when treating of their Inſtitute, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcourſing of the vtility therof, he ſayd in preſence of the Lord Condeſtable, and many others, who may remember it:
<hi>that if the Ieſuits had known him ſooner, they would haue loued him ſooner, and if he had knowne the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſooner, he would haue reeſtabliſhed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſooner.</hi> And another time, <hi>that if he were to be a Religious-man and liue a contemplatiue life, he would be a Carthuſian: and if he were to liue religiouſly in the world, and imploy him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in action, he would be a Ieſuite.</hi> This was at <hi>Bourg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fontaine,</hi> in the preſence of
<hi>Monſieur du Perron</hi> Lord <hi>de la Guette,</hi> and after of his priuy Counſell, a perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage whome his Maieſty honoured with a ſingular goodwill, togeather with a great eſtimation of his iudgment and wiſdome.</p>
               <p>Much more might be ſayd to this purpoſe, there being as many proofes of this great Princes good opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the <hi>Society,</hi> as there haue bin Panegyrikes and Apologyes heard made by him for this Order; yet my author contenteth himſefe with a piece of a letter written by his Maieſtie to the Mayor &amp; Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrats of <hi>Rochell</hi> in theſe wordes:
<hi>Chers &amp; bienaimeZ, ayant experimenté en pluſieurs villes de noſtre Royaume <pb n="32" facs="tcp:4752:17"/> la probité, ſuffiſance &amp; modestie des Peres Ieſuits, leſquels en leurs moeurs, doctrine &amp; commune conuerſation, font veoir, qu'ils n'ont rien deuant les yeux que l'honneur de Dieu: Nous auons trouué bon d'enuoyer en noſtre ville de la Rochelle pour y preſcher, le Pere Seguiran, Predicateur de leur Compagnie, reueſtu de toutes les qualiteZ, qui peuuent rendre vn homme digne de cette charge. En date du</hi> 17. <hi>de Septembre</hi> 1606. <hi>ſigné</hi> HENRY, <hi>&amp; plus bas, Ruzé.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Deare and welbeloued, hauing experienced in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Cittyes of our Kingdome the vertue, ſufficiency and modeſty of the Fathers of the Society, who in their behauiour, learning and common conuerſation doe declare that they haue nothing before their eyes but the honor of God: We haue thought good to ſend to our Citty of <hi>Rochell</hi> to preach, F. <hi>Seguiran</hi> a Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher of their Society, endued with all the qualityes, which may make a man worthy of this charge or of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice &amp;c. Dated the 17. of Septembre 1606. ſigned HENRY, and vnderneath, Ruzé.</p>
               <p>Now (ſaith my Author) who is ſo blind, that ſeeth not, or ſo wicked that graunteth not, that this onely iudgment ought to be of more force, then all the calumniations of the world? For this was written after he had heard a thouſand times, in a manner, all the euill of the
<hi>Society</hi> which is ſayd at this day, &amp; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he had exactly and carefully made triall of them.</p>
               <p>For concluſion of this point, I muſt not omit to tell you, that the decree againſt <hi>Chastel</hi> was not abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutly cenſured
<hi>at Rome,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pag. 42.</note> as <hi>Anti-Coton</hi> obiecteth: for the late king was certified by letters from thence, that they cenſured nothing belonging to the fact, <pb n="33" facs="tcp:4752:17"/> which they deteſted as much as any in <hi>France;</hi> but that which they cenſured, was a clauſe of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree defining and determining, what was hereſie, which appertayneth not to the Parliament of <hi>Paris,</hi> but to the Church of God, and the chiefe Paſtor thereof.</p>
               <p>Thus much for <hi>Chastell:</hi> after whom <hi>Anti-Coton</hi> returneth to one <hi>Barriere,</hi> who intended to haue mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered the late King before he was admitted to the Crowne by <hi>Paris</hi> and other Cittyes. And it ſeemeth,<note place="margin">Pag. 116.</note> that he imparted this his deſigne among others to F. <hi>Varade</hi> Rector of the Colledge of the
<hi>Society</hi> at <hi>Paris:</hi> which Citty being at that time in warre with his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty, the Father could not by any meanes giue aduiſe: &amp; yet my Author doth not altogether excuſe him in this as his Maieſtie himſelf ſeemed to do, cauſing him to be warned, that he ſhould depart from <hi>Paris,</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he was to come thither, and neuer calling him in que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion for it afterward. This is the moſt, that can be probably belieued againſt this Father. For the reſt, which <hi>Anti-Coton</hi> affirmeth, of his perſwading and adiuring <hi>Barriere</hi> by the Sacraments of Confeſſion &amp; Communion, conteyneth many abſurdities, contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions and falſifications, as my Author ſheweth: and it is certayne, that the R. Father <hi>Seraphin Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qui,</hi> who went to his Maieſtie expreſſely to diſcouer this plot, auouched, that <hi>Barriere</hi> himſelfe had told him, that a Father of the <hi>Society</hi> at <hi>Lions</hi> affirmed, that he could not enterpriſe the killing of the King without damning himſelfe. And his Maieſtie himſelf often teſtifyed, that he had firſt word of that attempt from one of the Fathers.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:4752:18"/>That which followeth of the
<hi>Ieſuits</hi> ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ning from cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber to chamber crying:<note place="margin">Pag. 119.</note> 
                  <hi>Surgefrater, agitur de reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gione; Riſe brother, our Religion is in daunger;</hi> is euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly conuinced to be falſe by the circumſtance of the time, ſince it is ſayd to haue byn betwixt 8. and 9. of the clock at night, when the Ieſuits vſe not to be in bed. And beſydes, if it had bin true, what could <hi>Anti-Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> or any other calumniator haue made of it? But he wanteth matter, which maketh him goe to the gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mer ſchollers, and accuſe them for making compoſitions againſt the King, before he was admitted, in time of the league, which may very well be true in part; but it is falſe, that after the reduction of <hi>Paris</hi> to the Kings obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, there was any ſuch matter, and much leſſe, that any was forbidden to pray for him: but many are yet liuing, who can teſtify, that there was earneſt prayer made for his proſperity, and in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culer the R. Father <hi>Clement du Puy,</hi> their Prouinciall in the Prouince of
<hi>France</hi> ordayned, that the Penſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of the colledg of
<hi>Clermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t,</hi> who were about 200. ſhould euery day in the morning ſay the prayer, <hi>Quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumus omnipotens Deus, vt famulus tuus Henricus Rex noſter &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pag. 121.</note>All the obiections, which are made againſt <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander Hayus</hi> a ſcottiſh Father, appeare ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly to be fictions, by his deliuery out of priſon; as likewiſe that which he addeth of the Fathers ſending children into farre countreys, ſince that he whom he nameth, dealt with no <hi>Ieſuit,</hi> (for the party charged as the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducer, was not of the <hi>Society</hi> at that time.) That which followeth were of more importance, if it were true; and therfore no meruayle though it be ſo eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently <pb n="35" facs="tcp:4752:18"/> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uinced of falſhood. <hi>Anti-Coton</hi> bringeth the Duke of <hi>Sully</hi> for a witneſſe, that this Noble man him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe perſwading the late King not to recall the <hi>Ieſuits,</hi> was anſwered by him, <hi>Giue me then ſecurity for my life;</hi> which my author, not without cauſe, calleth a ſlaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der died in crimſon. For the ſayd Duke hath teſtified, both before the Queene herſelfe, and the Lord Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor, and the Lord
<hi>Villeroy,</hi> and many others, and in particuler to F. <hi>Coton,</hi> that he remembreth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of that, which the <hi>Anti-Coton</hi> maketh him ſay to the King, or the King to him.</p>
               <p>After ſome other obiections concerning <hi>England,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pag. 123.</note> which I am reſolued to omit, at length he commeth to the Reuerend Father <hi>Baldwin</hi> now in the Tower, and is not afraid to affirme, that he had ſome intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence with <hi>Francis Rauaillac, who</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>had byn in</hi> Flanders <hi>ſomewhat before his curſed enterpriſe.</hi> Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as my Author ſheweth, that
<hi>Rauaillac</hi> was particuler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly aſked, whether he had byn at
<hi>Bruxels;</hi> to which he anſwered: <hi>that he was neuer out of the Kingdome, and that he knew not where</hi> Bruxels <hi>was.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>From <hi>England</hi> he goeth to <hi>Polonia,</hi> affirming,<note place="margin">pag. 124.</note> that the <hi>Ieſuits</hi> haue perſwaded that King to vſe ſuch viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, that he hath byn in danger to looſe his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: which my Author calleth a manifeſt falſhod, for
<hi>Polonia</hi> was neuer in the memory of man ſo proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous; nor euer King more beloued, and reſpected, or more peaceable in his Eſtates; yea he hath entred into <hi>Moſcouia,</hi> where at this preſent he obteyneth very great victories. And as for <hi>Sweden,</hi> euery man knoweth, that his vncle
<hi>Charles</hi> withholdeth it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all right &amp; iuſtice, not in reſpect of the <hi>Ieſuits,</hi> 
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:4752:19"/> about whome there was neuer any queſtion; but by reaſon of the Dukes hereſie and ambition: ſhewing by his proceeding (which is moſt certaine) that out of the Catholicke Church there is no true fayth at all.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Ibidem.</note>That which followeth of
<hi>Tranſiluania</hi> is a meere fiction; neyther can he produce any ſuch letter, as he feigneth of the Baron of <hi>Zerotin;</hi> neyther were the Fathers euer ſuſpected of any conſpiracy againſt that Prince; yea
<hi>F. Alfonſus Carillo</hi> was his Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarius, vntill he ſent home the Lady <hi>Catherine</hi> of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> and did put his coſen
<hi>Balthazar Battorius</hi> to death. And at this preſent al (beſides the heretikes) do much deſire that the Fathers of the <hi>Society</hi> may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to <hi>Coluſwar,</hi> otherwiſe called <hi>Claudiopolis,</hi> &amp; to <hi>Fayrwar</hi> otherwiſe called <hi>Alba-Iulia.</hi> By all which this ſlander is made manifeſt, but by nothing more, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by that, which is added, of putting one of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to death; for neuer any heard of any ſuch, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides <hi>F. Martin Laterna</hi> Confeſſarius to King
<hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen Battorius,</hi> who being ſent by his Maieſty into
<hi>Tranſiluania,</hi> was taken vpon the ſea, and put to death by the Pyrates of Duke <hi>Charles,</hi> who ſtyleth himſelf King of
<hi>Sweden.</hi> Becauſe this calumniator could find no colour to charge the
<hi>Society</hi> with any thing againſt the houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> he taketh a new courſe, and will needes giue the reaſon therof to be, becauſe their Generall is a <hi>Spaniard,</hi> to whome they vow blind o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience.<note place="margin">Pag. 78. 81. &amp; 125.</note> But my Author ſheweth, that it is falſe, that the Generals of the <hi>Society</hi> are always Spaniards, as appeareth by the laſt, who was of <hi>Liege;</hi> and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though this who is now, be a <hi>Neapolitan;</hi> yet he is of
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:4752:19"/> the noble houſe of <hi>Aquauiua,</hi> ſonne to the Duke of <hi>Atri,</hi> Vncle to the Cardinall <hi>Aquauiua</hi> now liuing; which family hath alway byn eſteemed to fauour the French. It is alſo vntrue, that in the <hi>Society</hi> the firſt vowes are made to F. General, but immediatly to the Superiours of that place, which in <hi>France</hi> are French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, who cannot be thought leſſe faythfull to their King, then the
<hi>Spaniardes</hi> to theirs: and how their vow of obedience is to be vnderſtood, hath bin al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready declared.</p>
               <p>There remayneth yet <hi>Venice,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pag.
126.</note> concerning which <hi>Anti-Coto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> chargeth the
<hi>Ieſuits</hi> to haue byn the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of the laſt troubles betwixt that Commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>-wealth &amp; the Pope: wheras it is manifeſt out of the bookes of Friar <hi>Paul</hi> &amp; the reſt of that crew, that the cauſe of thoſe difficulties were, for that his Holynes would not permit the reall libertyes, and perſonal immuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Church to be infringed and violated: for which cauſe he had impoſed a locall &amp; perſonall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terdict vpon that State. Neither did the Fathers of the <hi>Society</hi> proceed any further, then the <hi>Capuchins</hi> and <hi>Theatins,</hi> who tooke it not to belong to them, to cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure the Popes proceedinges, but rather to obey his Decrees, vntill the Common-wealth had made their remonſtrations, and ſupplications to his Holyneſſe. And wheras this calumniator addeth, that the
<hi>Ieſuits</hi> wrought againſt the Common-wealth at <hi>Rome;</hi> my Author ſheweth, that the late King of <hi>France</hi> (in all mens iudgments) a moſt iudicious Prince, comma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the proofes of this, and other obiections to be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xamined; but nothing could be gotten, but ſilence, as that renowned Prelate the Cardinall of <hi>Ioycuſe,</hi> to <pb n="38" facs="tcp:4752:20"/> whome this whole affaire was committed by his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty, can witneſſe.</p>
               <p>Finally the <hi>Society</hi> can be no more blamed for ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing legacies and lands in that State, then in any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or then all other Religious Orders: Yea, if we ſpeake of their houſe in <hi>Venice</hi> it ſelfe, it was not ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of any rent, or land whatſoeuer. And here my Author hath iuſt cauſe to wiſh all men to informe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues throughly of the truth before they giue eare to the calumniations and falſ reports which the enemies of the <hi>Society</hi> are wont to raiſe.
<q rend="margQuotes">This (ſayth he) was the leſſon, which our great
<hi>Henry</hi> gaue to all thoſe, whome he ſaw ill affected vnto them, ſaying often.</q> 
                  <hi>That it was ſufficient to know the Ieſuites, for to loue, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme, and defend them.</hi> In ſo much, as all the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and great Lords of <hi>France</hi> can teſtifie, that they haue often heard him ſpeake of the <hi>Society</hi> with ſuch great affection, and ſuch honorable commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as could be giuen to any Religious Order.</p>
               <p>Hauing thus wandred vp and downe forraine Countreys,<note place="margin">Pag. 128.</note> this Libeller returneth home to <hi>France,</hi> and for concluſion of his ſecond Chapter heapeth vp ten lyes in one narration, concerning the erection of a Colledge of the <hi>Society</hi> in
<hi>Orleans.</hi> Firſt, that they ſent one of their Fathers to preach in that Citty the time of Lent; wheras it is manifeſt, that this prouiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Preachers belongeth to the Biſhops themſelues; &amp; beſides he miſtaketh Lent for Aduent. Secondly he affirmeth, that the Cittizens were not well content, nor ſatisfied with the Fathers preaching; wheras it is certayne, that his Auditory was very great, and his ſermons much applauded; in ſo much, that he could <pb n="39" facs="tcp:4752:20"/> hardly excuſe himſelfe from preaching the next Lent alſo, although there was another very eloquent, and learned man appointed. Thirdly (ſaith <hi>Anti-Coton</hi>) in ſteed of ſtudying, this Fa. buſied his braines in ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching out and intertayning ſuch, as had yet in their hartes any remainder of the old leuen of the league. This is a moſt malicious lye, and ſuch an one, as on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the
<hi>Hugonots</hi> will belieue, whom the late King cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the leaguers of his time. And the truth is, that the Father was alwaies ordinarily eyther in the Church, or els in his chamber, as thoſe of the Lord Biſhops of
<hi>Orleans</hi> houſe, where he had his lodging, will teſtify. Fourthly (ſayth this calumniator) this <hi>Ieſuite</hi> gaue out, that it was the Kinges will, that they ſhould be eſtabliſhed in that Citty; wheras the King had diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patched his Letters Pate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts to this purpoſe aboue foure moneths before, and had ſent them to the Lord Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, and <hi>Mounſieur Decures.</hi> Fiftly he ſaith, that the <hi>Ieſuites</hi> talke was of driuing out the Monkes of S. <hi>Sampſon,</hi> that they might get their Church. But my Author anſwereth, that this treatie was in the behalfe of the Reuerent Fathers of <hi>S. Francis</hi> of <hi>Paula</hi> his Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, commonly called <hi>Minims</hi> or <hi>Bon-homs,</hi> &amp; that all was done with due and lawfull circumſtances, and with conſent of the parties: and if afterwardes ſome deſired, that it might be imployed for a Colledg of the
<hi>Society,</hi> it was with the ſame conditions. Sixt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, like vnto this is that which followeth of diſpla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing <hi>Monſieur</hi> the Mareſhall of
<hi>Chaſtres</hi> Gouernour of that Citty &amp;c. for there was no ſuch matter. Seue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, he addeth, that the Fathers vſed much importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity with the King to this effect: wheras it was his <pb n="40" facs="tcp:4752:21"/> Maieſties owne motion to prefer <hi>Orleans</hi> before <hi>Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tres,</hi> becauſe he thought that a Colledge would be more profitable in that Citty, in reſpect of certaine families, which were reported to haue changed their Religion not long before. Eightly, the next lye is, that his Maieſtie graunted this Colledge vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der condition, that the Cittizens ſhould be brought to giue their conſent: whereas in deed, there is no ſuch word in the Patents, which are abſolute, with commendation of the <hi>Society,</hi> and teſtimony of the good, which their Colledges cauſe in all partes. Ninthly he bringeth in one
<hi>Touruile</hi> an Aduocate, prouing that in <hi>France</hi> a man could not loue the King and the <hi>Ieſuites</hi> both: but this is altogether falſe, and it would proue, that neither the Cittyes, and Parla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which haue receaued, and do willingly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the <hi>Society,</hi> ſhould loue their King; yea that the late King loued not himſelf, ſince that he ſhewed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuch extraordinary kindnes &amp; fauours, founding the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Colledges in diuers places at his owne charges, and reſoluing to place them in all the principall Citties of his Kingdome. Finally he concludeth, that all the Cittizens concurred iointly in the ſame opinion, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding, that the <hi>Society</hi> ſhould not be admitted: wheras indeed they were neyther all of one opinion, nor gaue an abſolute deniall; but only excuſed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues for want of meanes, offering to receaue them willingly, if his Maieſtie would prouide for them. Neyther is it probable, that they would anſwer other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, vnleſſe we ſhould meaſure them by the <hi>Hugo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nots,</hi> who poſſeſſed that Citty in former times. And thus we ſee, that my Author had reaſon to affirme, <pb n="41" facs="tcp:4752:21"/> that <hi>Anti-Coton</hi> muſt needes be verie ſhameles, ſince that he calumniateth ſo impudently; and ill habitua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, ſince he doth it ſo often: and finally of little ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, ſince he doth it ſo foliſhly.</p>
               <p>In his third Chapter <hi>Anti-Coton</hi> goeth about to ſhew,<note place="margin">Pag. 145.</note> that the Fathers of the
<hi>Society</hi> were guilty of the murther of the late King of
<hi>France,</hi> which is ſo incredible a calumniation, and ſo eaſily conuinced by many teſtimonies, and circumſtances, that it is a wonder how any could be ſo impudent, as to auouch ſo manifeſt an vntruth: but yet let vs examine, at leaſt ſo much as may carry any colour of truth, of which ſorte, that which he affirmeth of Fa. <hi>Comelet</hi> is not; and the words of Fa. <hi>Hardy</hi> are wreſted to a wrong ſenſe, for he only affirmed, that Princes were ſubiect to death and other caſualties, as well as mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner men.</p>
               <p>In like manner that which he bringeth againſt Fa.
<hi>Gontier</hi> is only proued by the teſtimony of a dead man, or els by ſuch a witneſſe, as openly giueth him the lye, I meane <hi>Monſieur de la Grange</hi> Secretary to the Prince of <hi>Condie,</hi> and the matter is cleere in it ſelfe: for he maketh Fa. Rector at <hi>Perigeus,</hi> where thoſe wordes ſhould be ſpoken, Fa. <hi>Saphore,</hi> which is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>togeather falſe. <hi>Monſieur de Guron,</hi> whom he ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dereth to haue dealt with the Preachers in <hi>Paris,</hi> that they ſhould preach ſeditious doctrine, is a very vertuous and deuout gentleman, and will maintayne againſt him and al the world, that this is a meere ſlaunder: yea the Duke of <hi>Sully</hi> auoucheth, that it is moſt falſe, that euer the Curates of <hi>Paris</hi> came with any complaint to him, either in this, or any other matter. And if <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur <pb n="42" facs="tcp:4752:22"/> de Guron</hi> had giuen any ſuch ſeditious diſcourſes, they would haue byn publiſhed, aſwell as others of leſſe importance.</p>
               <p>But aboue all, the falſitie of this calumniation ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth, in that he maketh the late King not only to diſſemble the matter, but alſo to reward the chiefe malefactor by making (as he ſaith) F.
<hi>Gontier</hi> his Preacher, &amp; giuing him a penſion: both which are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo moſt falſe. For this Father was no more the Kings Preacher afterward, then he had byn before. And as for the penſion, not only he, but Fa. <hi>Coton</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe neuer had any, it being againſt the inſtitute of the <hi>Society,</hi> that any of them ſhould take any thing in recompence of the exerciſe of their function, &amp; much leſſe, that any of them in particuler ſhould haue any rent, reuenue, or penſion. True it is, that the late King eſteemed highly the rare qualities, and excellent talents of F. <hi>Gontier,</hi> and eſpecially his great zeale, courage, and conſtancie in Gods cauſe: and all that euer the Lord Mareſhall
<hi>Dernano</hi> ſayd of him, was; that he could haue deſired, that the remonſtrances made before his Maieſty at <hi>S. Geruas,</hi> had beene
<hi>in camera charitatis,</hi> as his words were, witneſſe the Queene Regent her ſelfe, who was preſent and heard them.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pag. 147.</note>Thus much for Fa.
<hi>Gontier:</hi> after who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>Anti-Coton</hi> commeth to Fa.
<hi>Aubigny,</hi> and is not aſhamed to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouch that <hi>Rauaillac</hi> iuſtified vnto this Father, that he had told him in confeſſion of his intention to giue a great ſtroke, ſhewing him the knife, hauing an Heart engraue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vpon it; wheras the Regiſters of the Court it ſelfe do witneſſe, that <hi>Rauaillac</hi> being demanded a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <pb n="43" facs="tcp:4752:22"/> 
                  <hi>F. de Aubigny,</hi> anſwered, that he came to him one day after Maſſe in the month of <hi>Ianuary,</hi> he being in the Church, &amp; that he declared vnto him certaine viſions: and he depoſed, that the ſaid Father anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him, that he ſhould make no account of them, fearing leaſt his head were crazed; willing him to ſay his beades, and that if he had any thing to ſay to the King, he ſhould go to ſome Noble man to procure audience. Vpon which the ſaid Father and he being confronted the eighteenth of <hi>May,</hi> he charged him not with any other thing, only adding, that the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther had bidden him to haue care of his braine, and to eate ſome good broathes, that he might be able to ſleepe. And the day before, the Iudges hauing enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of him, whether he had not demanded of <hi>F. de Aubigny,</hi> if he ought not to confeſſe ſuch viſions, as exceeded the common courſe, and namely about kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Kings: the ſayd offender anſwered, noe. Being dema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded, whether he had no other ſpeach with him, and if he neuer ſaw him but that time: he likewiſe anſwered, noe. Being demanded againe, when the Father was preſent, why he went rather to him then to any other: he anſwered; Becauſe he had vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, that this Father was a friend to the brother of a certaine Religious Woman.</p>
               <p>Beſides at other times being vrged by the Iudges to declare thoſe, who had any way aſſiſted him in this crime, or to whome he had imparted his purpoſe: his anſwere was, that ſince his being in priſon many had prouoked him to make this acknowledgment, and in particuler the Lord Archbiſhop of <hi>Aix:</hi> but he was neuer mooued by any, neither did euer any ſpeake <pb n="44" facs="tcp:4752:23"/> with him of any ſuch matter. And the 27. of
<hi>May</hi> his ſentence being pronounced, and he exhorted to preuent the torment by confeſſing the complices, he tooke it vpon his ſoule, that neither man, nor wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, or any other beſides himſelfe knew of it. And being laid vpon the torment, he beſeeched God with a loud voice to haue pitty of his ſoule, and to pardon his offence; but yet not otherwiſe, then if he had not concealed any thing. Which he often repeated after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward vnder the oath, which he had made vnto God and the Court. And before he was deliuered to the Doctors, he likewiſe ſayd, that he was not ſo miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to retaine any thing: if he had not declared it al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready: knowing well, that he could not obtaine that mercy of God which he expected, if he ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceale any thing, and that he would not haue indured the torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t inflicted vpon him, if he had knowne any thing more. And being in the hands of <hi>M. Gamache</hi> and
<hi>M. Filſacke</hi> Doctors of the <hi>Sorbon,</hi> he gaue them leaue to reueale his Confeſſion, and to print it alſo; that it might be made knowne to all, which the ſaid Doctors declared to be: That none but he had giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the blow, that he had not byn intreated, ſollicited, nor induced by any, neither had he imparted the matter to any. He acknowledged that he had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted a great fault, for which he hoped mercy at Gods handes, it being greater then his ſinne, but that he would not expect any, if he had concealed any thing. And finally, immediatly before his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xecution, he confirmed with an oath, that he had diſcouered all, and that not any in the world had induced him, nor he ſpoken, or imparted the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <pb n="45" facs="tcp:4752:23"/> to others. And he alwayes perſiſted ſaying the ſame in the middeſt of his torments: yea after he had byn drawn halfe an houre with horſes, he not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding perſeuered in this deniall.</p>
               <p>That which <hi>Anti-Coton</hi> ſaith of the Preachers,<note place="margin">Pag. 150.</note> who might ſeeme to haue moued him, is a meere fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: for he neuer made mention of them, but when he affirmed, that if he were ſo much forſake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by God, as to dy without declaring his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plices, he would not thinke to be ſaued, nor that there was any paradiſe for him: becauſe ſaith he, <hi>Abyſſus abyſſum inuocat,</hi> as he had learned of the Preachers, and therfore this would be to double his offence. Beſides if he had blamed the Preachers, as <hi>Anti-Coton</hi> affirmeth; he could not meane thoſe of <hi>Paris,</hi> ſince that it appeareth by his confeſſion, that he departed from <hi>Angouleſme</hi> the laſt tyme but one of his being there, 13. daies before Chriſtmas, and returned againe before Lent: ſince that, he confeſſed and communicated at
<hi>Angouleſme</hi> the firſt ſonday in Lent, and did not ſet forward from thence to <hi>Paris,</hi> vntill Eaſter day; and came not to
<hi>Paris</hi> vntill a weeke after: by which it appeareth, that he was not in
<hi>Paris</hi> in the time either of Aduent, or Lent. And finally this accuſation belongeth no more to the <hi>Ieſuites,</hi> then to all other Preachers, and may be applied by a Calumniator to any of them in particuler.</p>
               <p>It were but a folly to ſtand vpon that reporte,<note place="margin">Pag. 158.</note> which he affirmeth to haue byn of the Kinges death at <hi>Prage</hi> and <hi>Bruxells</hi> a weeke or fortnight before it happned. For to omit the like examples, which my Author produceth, who ſeeth not, that ſuch rumours <pb n="46" facs="tcp:4752:24"/> vſe to runne vpon diuers occaſions? though indeed the letters which <hi>Anti-Coton</hi> alledgeth from
<hi>Prage</hi> to this effect, are feigned, as the ſonne of him to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they were ſaid to be written, teſtifieth. The Prouoſt of <hi>Petiuiers</hi> affirmed by this Calumniator to haue byn in faction a <hi>Ieſuit,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pag. 160.</note> doth not any way belong to them; and was as deuout, as <hi>Anti-Coton</hi> himſelfe ſeemeth to be, not hauing byn at Confeſſion for the ſpace of eight yeares.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pag. 161.</note>The ſmiling countenance, which this ſlaunderer attributeth to the Fathers, were indeed true teares, as thoſe, to whom they imparted their griefes, can teſtifie: and when they were preſented by <hi>Monſieur de la Varanne,</hi> who was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded by the Queene her ſelfe to bring them, F. <hi>Coton</hi> who ſpake in all their names, was interrupted with his owne and the other Fathers ſighes and teares.</p>
               <p>It is alſo falſe, which ſome giue out, that a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall perſonage, and officer ſhould will them when they went to <hi>Fleche</hi> (to carry the Kings hart) not to forget the tooth which <hi>Chaſtell</hi> had ſtrook out ſome yeares before. For the Fathers did not ſo much as ſee, or ſpeake with that perſonage, and he was to wiſe to let any ſuch words eſcape him. No leſſe fooliſh, and falſe is the next obiection concerning the Fathers be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing abſent from the Kings Funerall, as appeareth by the certification which followeth: <hi>I the vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>written do certifie thoſe, to whome it appertaineth, that the Fathers of the</hi> Society <hi>reſiding in</hi> Paris, <hi>came togea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to</hi> S. Germain of Auxerois, <hi>which was the place appointed for the orders of Religion to meet in, the day of the Funerall of the late King, the great Henry the fourth, <pb n="47" facs="tcp:4752:24"/> and preſented themſelues to me, that they might haue a place among the reſt of thoſe, who aſsiſted in the Funerals: which was denied the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, leaſt it might cauſe confuſion, ſince they were not inſerted in my roll, becauſe it is not their cuſtome to aſsiſt in ſuch actions any more then the</hi> Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thuſians <hi>&amp;</hi> Celeſtines. <hi>Which when the ſayd Fathers had vnderſtood, they went to the</hi> Louure, <hi>and into the Hall, where the body with his partraiture lay, and there they ſprinkled holy water vpon it, and prayed for the ſoule of his Maiestie. Dated in</hi> Paris
<hi>the</hi> 29. <hi>of September,</hi> 1610. Guiot Rhodes <hi>Great Maister of the Cerimonies of</hi> France.</p>
               <p>There remaineth yet the obiection of <hi>Monſieur</hi> the Mareſhall of <hi>Chastres,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pag. 164.</note> Generall of the forces ſent from <hi>France</hi> to <hi>Cleues,</hi> whom
<hi>Anti-Coton</hi> affirmeth to haue beene diſwaded from that iourney by the
<hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits.</hi> But this Nobleman hath diſcharged them fully and plainly from this calumniation in the preſence of the Queene Regent, the Earle of
<hi>Soiſſons,</hi> and of all the Court; and beſides hath giuen the Fathers a teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony to the contrary vnder his owne hand. Thus this Calumniator endeth his third Chapter, and in the fourth I find nothing to this purpoſe.</p>
               <p>In the fifth he inueigheth chiefly againſt F. <hi>Coton</hi> in particuler,<note place="margin">Pag. 243.</note> only at the later end he hath an obiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or two concerning the riches &amp; want of learning of the
<hi>Society</hi> in France. To which my Author anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth briefly, that excepting the Colledge of <hi>Fleche</hi> which was founded &amp; endowed by the late King, there is not any houſe in all France, in which euery one may haue allotted twentie pounds for his expen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces by the yeare, accompting not only their meate, <pb n="48" facs="tcp:4752:25"/> drinke, &amp; apparell, but alſo their Libraries, Infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maries, Sacriſties, Viaticums, intertayning of ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and other publike charges. In proofe whereof, and for preuention of this ſlaunder, <hi>Fa. Coton</hi> hath giuen a note of all the goods, which the
<hi>Society</hi> hath in <hi>France,</hi> to the Lo. Chauncellour, the Lo. of
<hi>Sully</hi> and the Secretaries of Eſtate, graunting &amp; yeilding all that is not ſpecified in that Roll, to any that can find it out. And whereas
<hi>Anti-Coton</hi> ſpeaketh of aboue an hundred thouſand Crownes in rent, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured by the <hi>Society</hi> in the ſpace of ſeauen or eight yeares ſince their Reuocation: My Author in his owne and the reſt of the Fathers names, maketh a free gift and donation to him of all, that ſhalbe found to belong to the <hi>Society</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> ſurmounting the ſumme of fifty thouſand, vpon this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dition, that he will ſupply ſo much, as wanteth to make vp that ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me. And as for the Nouiſhip in the Suburbs of
<hi>S. Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main,</hi> within the precincts wherof <hi>Anti-Coton</hi> ſaith a prety Towne might ſtand: the truth is, that the whole houſe, courts, and gardens are not aboue 30. fadome ſquare.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pag. 247.</note>Finally he concludeth his whole rayling diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe with telling vs, that the Fathers of the
<hi>Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety</hi> are ignorant perſons, and will ouerthrow lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and is not aſhamed to charge the Lord Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall <hi>Peron,</hi> as Authour of this ſlaunder. But it were a folly to ſay any thing in the diſproof therof, the whole world being witneſſe to the contrary, which would farre ſooner approue that <hi>encomium</hi> of the Lo. Abbot of <hi>Tiron,</hi> who as
<hi>Monſieur Yuete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aux</hi> the Kings maſter reporteth, was wont to ſay, that <pb n="49" facs="tcp:4752:25"/> 
                  <hi>Imperium litterarum eſt penes Ieſuitas.</hi> The empire of learning is among the <hi>Ieſuits.</hi> And the concourſe of ſchollers to their Schooles doth teſtify the ſame, which this fooliſh fellow would perſwade men to proceede from not taking any thing, eyther for waſhing or for candles: as though the flower of the nobility would be moued with ſuch toyes: and this could be a motiue for ſo many Parents, as in time of the Fathers abſence from <hi>France,</hi> ſent their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to their Schooles in other Countries.</p>
               <p>For concluſion of this Paragraph it will not be amiſſe to note, how falſly <hi>Anti-Coton</hi> in his Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle Dedicatory to the Queene Regent, auoucheth theſe his calumniatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the <hi>Society,</hi> to be the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of her Maieſties higheſt Courts of Iuſtice, the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent of the greateſt part of her Cleargy, &amp; among them, euen of the Sacred Faculty of Diuinity, and in a word the common vniuerſall outcry of all her people. For it appeareth by that, which hath bene ſaid, that this is ſo farre from being true, that no one honeſt, or ciuill man can be produced for the proofe of any one of theſe ſlaunders. And beſides my Author noteth, that the Regiſters, &amp; procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinges of the Court conuince the contrary.<note place="margin">Pag. 21.</note> To which he addeth the funerall orations of <hi>Monſieur d'Angeres, Monſieur de Ries,</hi> and
<hi>Monſieur d' Ayre:</hi> the atteſtations of <hi>Monſieur de Paris:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pag. 309.</note> the deputation which the Cleargy hath lately made in the perſon of my Lo. Archbiſhop of <hi>Ambrun</hi> for the aſſiſtance of the reeſtabliſhment of the Colledge of
<hi>Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mont:</hi> the aſſembly of the Doctors of the <hi>Sorbone</hi> the
23. of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> and thoſe of the two Faculties of Phiſick, and the Cannon Law in the moneth of <pb n="50" facs="tcp:4752:26"/> 
                  <hi>September</hi> following, the yeare 1610. in which they agreed that the Fathers of the
<hi>Society</hi> ſhould teach with them in <hi>Paris,</hi> being incorporated to the Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſity.<note place="margin">Pag. 306.</note> All which we might finally confirme with the Letters Pate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of this King; for the eſtabliſhing of all that, which his Father granted in fauour of the
<hi>Society.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>THE SOLVTIONS OF the obiections againſt <hi>Fa. Coton</hi> in particuler. <hi>§. III.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HITHERTO we haue ſeene what <hi>Anti-Coton</hi> was able to ſay againſt the <hi>Society</hi> in generall: now we come to <hi>F. Coton</hi> in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticuler, againſt whom this malicious mate ſheweth exceeding great ſpite and malice; but with no more truth nor probability, then we haue found hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to.<note place="margin">Pag. 134.</note> And firſt he chargeth him with certain interro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations made to a certain poſſeſſed perſon, which he affirmeth that the Father himſelfe had written in a ticket, and through ouerſight had giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them to <hi>Monſieur Gillot</hi> a Counſelour, in a booke which he had lent him: But my Author conuinceth this ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>niation to be falſe by many reaſons. For firſt the exorciſmes of this maid were publicke, and before many at <hi>S. Victor,</hi> at <hi>S. Genouefa,</hi> and at <hi>S. Nicolas du Chardonet,</hi> &amp; therfore there would not want witnes of theſe interrogations, if there had beene any ſuch. Secondly it is denied, that euer <hi>Monſieur Gillot</hi> lent any booke to F. <hi>Coton,</hi> neither doth the Father re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, <pb n="51" facs="tcp:4752:26"/> that euer he ſaw him, and much leſſe is it likely that he had any familiarity with him, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially hauing often heard, that he had alway ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed himſelfe an earneſt enemy to the <hi>Society,</hi> though without all cauſe. Thirdly when this fable was tould the late King by a Noble man of the preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded reformed Religion, the ſaid Father offered to giue another writing of his owne hand, that it might be confronted with that ticket, which not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding would not be accepted. And <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur du Perron</hi> one of the Kings priuie Counſell ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing conſidered the ticket attentiuely, maintayned that it was not Fa. <hi>Cotons</hi> hand, from whom he had ſeene &amp; receyued many letters. Fourthly theſe falſe witneſſes are at variance among themſelues, for ſome of them make theſe interrogations mount to the number of 30. 40. 50. 60. and more, as may be ſeene in diuers printed copies; others make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be fewer, and <hi>Anti-Coton</hi> himſelfe hath not only not ſpecified more then 5. but alſo by calling the paper wherin they were written, a ticket, ſheweth that they could not be many more, and therefore no meruaile, though the late King vſed to ieſt at the matter, ſaying: that it would proue like the libra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of <hi>Madame de Mont penſier.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And that which is added, that Fa. <hi>Coton</hi> went to theſe exorciſmes moued with curioſitie, is as falſe; for he was oftener then once commaunded by the Queene, who dealt with the Lo. Biſhop of
<hi>Paris</hi> to that end; and yet the Fa. yeelded not, before he had repreſented ſome difficulties, which he found in the matter. By which it appeareth, that he was not dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen <pb n="52" facs="tcp:4752:27"/> by any curioſity, and much leſſe by any famili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aritie he had with ſpirits, as this impudent Fellow is not aſhamed to ſuſpect; and vpon theſe fooliſh ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions to make very odious illatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s againſt him, which redound no leſſe to the iniurie of the late King, as my Author ſheweth. But that there was no ſuch curioſity, familiaritie, nor interrogations, might be proued by the Paſtors &amp; Religious me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the places, where theſe exorciſmes were made. To whom we may adde <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur Forget</hi> a Doctor of <hi>Sorbo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> and many Princes and Lordes of the Court, to omit the reſt. And finally the Lord Biſhop of <hi>Paris</hi> knoweth, that
<hi>Monſieur de La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ual</hi> was Catholike, before Fa. <hi>Coto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s</hi> going to theſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orciſmes; and therfore it is incredible, that the Fa. would demaund what ſhould be the iſſue of his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion, which notwithſtanding <hi>Anti-Coton</hi> ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth downe in the firſt place.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pag. 140.</note>The next obiection concerning the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> who ſhould come addreſſed to Fa. <hi>Coton,</hi> with intention to kill the King; is ſuch an impudent, and incredible ſlaunder, that it deſerueth no anſwere, ſince that it is againſt all reaſon and ſenſe, that <hi>Fa. Coton,</hi> or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other of his coate ſhould conſent to the death of him, who had been ſo great a fauourer and promotor of their whole Order. And beſides <hi>Monſieur de Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menye</hi> Secretary of Eſtate, and in particuler of the Kingdome of <hi>Nauar</hi> &amp; of <hi>Bearne,</hi> hath teſtified in the preſence of the Lord Biſhops of <hi>Maſcon,</hi> and <hi>Siſteron,</hi> that al the letters of
<hi>Monſieur de la Forze</hi> Lieutena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for the King in <hi>Bearne</hi> paſſed through his ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, &amp; that he neuer ſaw any ſuch matter in them, out of which not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, this calumniation is only auouched.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:4752:27"/>Thirdly <hi>Anti-Coton</hi> obiecteth, that F. <hi>Coton</hi> had written the late Kinges Confeſſion into
<hi>Spaine,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pag. 142.</note> and for that cauſe was in diſgrace the ſpace of 6. weekes: And that the yong King, who now is, hearing ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, ſaied to the Father, that he vvould tell him nothing, becauſe he vvould write it into <hi>Spaine,</hi> as he had donne his Fathers Confeſſion. But firſt noe man euer perceaued, that Fa. <hi>Coton</hi> was in diſgrace with the late King for the ſpace of 6. houres, neyther were it any way probable, that his Maieſtie would haue contynued to confeſſe vnto him, vntill his dying day, if he had either knowen, or ſuſpected any ſuch matter. True it is, that F. <hi>Coton</hi> himſelfe requeſted the King oftentimes to make choice of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other Confeſſarius, &amp; in particuler of the Lo. Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop of <hi>Ambrun,</hi> by reaſon of his great vertue, and ſingular pietie, vſing the help of his brother alſo to that end: but his Maieſty anſwered him twice, that he would neuer take any other. And ſurely it is ſtrange to ſee, how this Calumniator is not aſhamed to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe Fa. <hi>Coton</hi> now of reuealing the Kinges Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, no more then he was before to charge Fa. <hi>Fron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> with a ſpeach which might ſeeme too ſtrict and rigorous in this point. As for that of the yong King, the Queene herſelfe hath taken the paines to make inquiry, being aſtoniſhed to heare ſo ſtrange a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port. And ſhe hath found the truth to be, that his Maieſtie neuer heard of any ſuch matter, &amp; much leſſe vſed any ſuch words to Fa. <hi>Coton,</hi> who retay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the ſame place now, which he had before in his Fathers time.</p>
               <p>Fourthly this Calumniator addeth,<note place="margin">Pag.
150.</note> that Fa. <pb n="54" facs="tcp:4752:28"/> 
                  <hi>Coton</hi> hauing obtayned leaue to ſpeake with <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaillac</hi> in priſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, bid him take heed, leaſt he did accuſe the innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, fearing leaſt he would accuſe the
<hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits.</hi> But firſt Fa. <hi>Coton</hi> went not to the priſon of his owne accord, but by the Queenes commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as all the Court knoweth. Secondly he v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed no ſuch wordes to <hi>Rauaillac,</hi> but that vnfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate wretch complayning, that they would make him accuſe either the
<hi>Ieſuits,</hi> or the Princes to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he had neuer imparted his deſigne; the Fa. replied in theſe wordes: <hi>Thou deceaueſt thy ſelfe, none would haue thee to accuſe the innocent, but euery one deſireth that thou ſhouldeſt ſay the truth. And as thou ſhouldeſt be in the way of damnation, by accuſing the innocent: ſo likewiſe thou ſhalt be in the ſame caſe, vnleſſe thou reuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt the culpable. Thou muſt tell the truth, if thou deſireſt to ſee his face who hath ſaid; I am the way, the truth, &amp; the life.</hi> And of this are witneſſes all, that were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent at that time, who can alſo teſtifie (which this Calumniator was loath to ſpeake of) that the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable Parricide was moued by Fa.
<hi>Cotons</hi> ſpeaches to acknowledge his fault, which he had not done till then; and to ſhed aboundant teares, deſiring to haue a Confeſſarius, by which occaſion the Fa. ſaid vnto him: <hi>If thou hadſt imparted thy tentation to a good Confeſſarius, he would haue vſed the ſame reaſons and perſwaſions to thee which thou hast heard of me: he would haue made thee to haue knowne thy ſinne, and haue perſwaded thee to haue giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it ouer.</hi> To which the poore wretch anſwered: <hi>To whome would you haue had me gone to Confeſsion? he would haue accuſed me, and cauſed my death. Thou deceaueſt thy ſelfe</hi> (ſaid the Father) <hi>a <pb n="55" facs="tcp:4752:28"/> prudent Confeſſarius would haue diuerted thee from this heynous cryme, he would haue put the life of the King in ſecuritie, and thine alſo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now we come to the laſt Chapter of <hi>Anti-Coto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:</hi> for I think not any thing which he ſaith in his fourth Chapter concerning Fa.
<hi>Cotons</hi> booke, worth the noting, vnleſſe I ſhould tell you of that lye and ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, wherin he auoucheth, that the King comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>F. Coton</hi> to write againſt <hi>F. Mariana;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pag.
43.</note> which my Author denieth, and diſproueth at large in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of his booke: wherfore omitting this, let vs come to that obiection concerning his liuing in the Court,<note place="margin">Pag. 223.</note> which he ſayth is a ſcandall to the whole Church, being a thing contrary, not only to the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of all Monkes, but particulerly to the Rules of the
<hi>Ieſuits.</hi> And Cardinall <hi>Tolet</hi> houlds it for a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall truth, that a Religious perſon, who liueth in the Court is excommunicate, albeit he hath leaue of his Superiour.</p>
               <p>To which my Author anſwereth, that in the third Article of the
<hi>Societies</hi> eſtabliſhment in <hi>France,</hi> approued by the late King, his Counſell, and Court of Parlament; it is ordeined, that thoſe of the <hi>Society</hi> ſhall haue ordinarily one of their Order about the King, and he muſt be a Frenchman, with ſufficient authority to ſerue his Maieſty as a Preacher, and to informe him of their proceedings, as occaſion ſhall be offered. Wherefore if <hi>F. Coton</hi> ſhould depart from the Court, another of the ſame <hi>Society</hi> muſt neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily come in his place. Secondly my Author ſaith, that the Fathers of the <hi>Society</hi> are no monkes; yea their Inſtitute and functions are altogeather differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:4752:29"/> from thoſe, which a ſolitary life requireth; and to this end, he alleageth the ſecond and third Rule of the Su<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary of your Conſtitutions: <hi>The end of this</hi> Society <hi>is to attend with Gods grace, not only to their owne ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation and perfection, but alſo with the ſame grace to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy themſelues with all their forces, to the ſaluation and perfection of their neighbours.</hi> And a little after: <hi>It is proper to our vocation to paſſe into diuers countries, and to liue in any place of the world, where Gods greater ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, and the help of ſoules is hoped for.</hi> According to which (ſayth my Author) we haue ſeene, and by Gods help ſhall ſee, what great fruit the <hi>Societie</hi> hath produced in the conuerſion of Infidels, in the redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of hereticks, and the inſtruction of Catholicks. And this is that (ſaith he) which <hi>Monſieur</hi> the Prince anſwered very wiſely not long ſince to one, who would haue diſguſted him with the Ieſuits. <hi>Theſe peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi> (ſaid he)
<hi>carry the faith thither, where it is not, &amp; maintayne it, where it is; for which cauſe I will allvvaies loue them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After this my Author ſheweth at large, how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that were Monkes, haue left their Cloiſtres for the good of ſoules. As for example
<hi>S. Baſil,</hi> and <hi>S. Gregory, S. Auguſtine</hi> and <hi>S. Hierome,</hi> S. <hi>Remigius</hi> &amp; <hi>S. Martin, S. Auguſtine</hi> of England and his fower Companions ſent thither by S. <hi>Gregory</hi> the Great; S. <hi>Lambert</hi> and S. <hi>Kilian,</hi> S. <hi>Wilfrid,</hi> S.
<hi>Willebrord,</hi> and S. <hi>Svvitbert;</hi> ſo that though Fa.
<hi>Coton</hi> were a Monk, yet he might well be excuſed by theſe examples, noe leſſe then thoſe foure of the ſame <hi>Society,</hi> which ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company the King of <hi>Poland,</hi> one of them being his Confeſſarius, and another his Preacher; as alſo the <pb n="57" facs="tcp:4752:29"/> Confeſſarius to the Queene of <hi>Spaine,</hi> to the Duke of <hi>Bauaria,</hi> to the Dutcheſſes of <hi>Mantua,</hi> &amp; <hi>Lorayn;</hi> &amp; finally to the Archduke <hi>Matthias,</hi> now King of <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary.</hi> Neyther do there want examples of other Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious orders in the ſame kind; for the Confeſſarius of the Queene Regent is of <hi>S. Auguſtines</hi> order: the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> and the Archduke of <hi>Flanders</hi> vſe to confeſſe to Religious men of <hi>S. Dominicks,</hi> &amp; the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fanta to one of <hi>S. Francis,</hi> to omit the reſt.</p>
               <p>As for the Authority of <hi>Cardinall Tolet,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Inſtr. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerd. l. 1. c. 40.</note> which he obiecteth againſt F. <hi>Cotons</hi> being in the Court, my Author anſwereth, that in the place by him alledged, there is noe ſuch matter. But yet I haue been a little more curious to ſee, if I could find, vpon what ground <hi>Anti-Coton</hi> could gather any ſuch doctrine out of that learned Cardinall; and I haue found, that it is a manifeſt falſification. For in the Chapter im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly going before, Monks &amp; Chano<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Regulars,<note place="margin">Cap. 39.</note> not hauing adminiſtration, which preſume to goe to the Courts of Princes, for the harme of their Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries or Prelats, are ſayd to incurre excommunicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. But for declaration thereof, <hi>Tolet</hi> preſently no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth out of the Gloſſe vpon that text of Canon law,<note place="margin">Clement, <hi>Nem agro</hi> de ſtat. Monach, § <hi>Quia verò.</hi>
                  </note> where this excommunication is expreſſed, that two things are required for thoſe Monks &amp; Chano<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars to incurre this cenſure. Firſt, that they enter into the Court. Secondly, that they enter with this minde, whether they haue their Prelats leaue or not. Now then this Calumniator ſhould haue ſhewed, that <hi>F. Coton</hi> had any ſuch intention, from which he is ſo free, that the only naming of that condition would haue cleared him of all ſuch ſuſpicions; which <hi>Anti-Coton</hi>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:4752:30"/> ſeemed to forſee, &amp; therefore falſified the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals authoritie.</p>
               <p>The other perſonall imputations againſt <hi>F. Coton</hi> are either moſt impudent lyes, without all ſhew of truth, or els meere ſuſpicions, grounded vpon ſuch co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectures as any indifferent man would rather inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prete to the Fathers commendation.<note place="margin">Pag. 229.
240. 241.</note> Such are the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iections, which are taken out of his letter to a very deuout and religious woman, and his Booke of deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dedicated to the Queene her ſelfe. And it is ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for confutation of all theſe ſlaunders, that there cannot be any one produced, or named in the whole Court who will teſtify any the leaſt miſdemeanour of him: for if there were any ſuch, it is not likely, that he, who hath not ſpared the king himſelf, would paſſe them ouer in ſilence, or leauing the Court would run to
<hi>Auignion</hi> &amp; <hi>Languedoc</hi> to find matter. Which notwithſtanding he doth with ſo euill ſucceſſe, that the whole Cittyes haue ioyned and giuen their teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony againſt him: and not only they, but euen the Abbot of <hi>Boys</hi> whome he preſumed to father his ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumniation vpon, hath openly diſclaimed and diſpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued him. For thus he writeth in a teſtification, which he ſent to <hi>F. Coton</hi> himſelfe:<note place="margin">Pag. 231.</note> 
                  <hi>I the vnderwritten do te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtify, that I was in</hi> Auignion <hi>all the time, that the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerend Fa.</hi> Coton <hi>of the Society of</hi> Ieſus <hi>remained there, and I neuer heard any ſay, that he committed any thing contrary to the dignity, &amp; quality of his profeſsion; which I affirme of that in particuler, wherof the</hi> Anti-Coton <hi>accuſeth him. And becauſe I am made the Author of ſo manifeſt a ſlaunder, I ſay freely, that I know no ſuch mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and that I haue alwaies knowne the ſayd Reuerend</hi> F.
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:4752:30"/> Coton <hi>to be a venerable, and good Religious man. In testimony wherof, I haue written and ſubſcribed this my preſent depoſition at</hi> Paris <hi>in my ſtudy, this Vigill of</hi> S. Denys
<hi>Martyr</hi> 1610.</p>
               <p>The Abbot of Boys Oliuier.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And haue ſealed it with my ſeale.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After this, follow in my Author 4.<note place="margin">Pag. 232. &amp; ſeq.</note> other atteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Vicar Generall, the Clergy, and the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuls of <hi>Auignion,</hi> and alſo of the Biſhop of
<hi>Orange,</hi> all which do teſtifie, that they knew <hi>Fa. Coto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> all the time of his being in that Cytty, and that there was neuer any ſuch matter, as the <hi>Anti-Coton</hi> chargeth him withall; but contrariwiſe, that they all receiued great contentment, edification and benefit by his learned Sermons, and other pious and holy endeauours. All which atteſtations were afterward examined, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued by the Kings Notaries in
<hi>Paris.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To the like effect is the Atteſtation of aboue 30.<note place="margin">Pag. 312.</note> of the moſt principall perſons in
<hi>Languedoc,</hi> and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in the Citty of <hi>Nimes;</hi> all which do teſtifie, that both the publicke,<note place="margin">Pag. 317.</note> and priuate actions of <hi>Fa. Coton</hi> did all way tend to the honour &amp; glory of God, and the edification and comfort of others: and that he alwaies behaued himſelfe very piouſly, religiouſly, and charitably, aſwell in his Sermons, Exhortations and Catechiſmes, as alſo in viſiting the ſicke, aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting the afflicted, and comforting the poore: in ſo much, that by his meanes, inſtruction, learning, and good life (after Gods grace) the faith, deuotion, cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and other vertues of the Catholick, Apoſtolick, and Roman Religion haue beene increaſed, and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gmented in the ſame Citty; in which the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance <pb n="60" facs="tcp:4752:31"/> of ciuill warres had cauſed ſome diminution, and decreaſe. And that they neuer heard, nor vnderſtood any ſuſpition of any euil, ſca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dalous, or culpable beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour in the perſon, or actions of the ſaid Reuerend <hi>Fa. Coton:</hi> Yea they add, that by his publick Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, and priuate counſailes and admonitions, he maintained, confirmed, and conſerued that Citty in peace, amity, and fraternall ſociety; and ſtirred vp a holy emulation to do good one to another, without partiality, or diſtinction; and by good examples, &amp; mutuall courteſies to bury the memory of ciuill wars, and the exacerbations, and offences, which the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iury of former times might haue cauſed.</p>
               <p>Much more might be ſaid in iuſtification, and commendation of <hi>Fa. Coton,</hi> by declaring his vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous education from his very childhood,<note place="margin">Pag. 222.</note> of which there be many eye witneſſes in <hi>Paris</hi> it ſelfe. At the age of eighteene yeares he entred into the <hi>Society,</hi> where my Author proteſteth hefore God and his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, that he hath byn accompted alway, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out exception, one of the beſt Religious men of his Order. But I will conclude with the praiſe, which the late King was wont to giue him, often affirming, that Fa. Coton
<hi>was the moſt humble,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pag. 241.</note> 
                  <hi>and modeſt ſpirit, that euer he knew:</hi> which commendation <hi>Monſieur du Perron</hi> Lord of <hi>Guette,</hi> and a priuy Counſelour will witneſſe, that he heard of his Maieſty the laſt Eaſter before his death. And the truth is, that if he were otherwiſe, he could neuer haue continued in the Court with ſuch eſtimation, and good will of the Princes, and principall perſonages. For as <hi>Monſieur de la Forze</hi> told him one day before the King,<note place="margin">Pag. 221.</note> he had
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:4752:31"/> need to take heed, how he did walke, for if he ſhould chance to ſtumble, there would not want thoſe, that would take him vp.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>A BRIEFE NOTE Of the doctrine, and proceedings of
<hi>Anti-Coton</hi> and other <hi>Hugonots. §. IIII.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BY occaſion of the obiections and calumnia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which
<hi>Anti-Coton</hi> hath heaped to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geather againſt the <hi>Society,</hi> my Author hath been inforced to touch ſomething in the ſame kind againſt him and his fellow-<hi>Hugonots:</hi> but yet with ſuch modeſtie, and moderation, that he hath not intermedled with any their perſonall crimes, but only with ſuch errours, as are committed in this booke which he anſwereth, or belong to thoſe poynts of doctrine, which are imputed, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected againſt the <hi>Society,</hi> that is, concerning <hi>Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocation,</hi> and
<hi>the killing of Kinges.</hi> For the third of the ſecrecy of Confeſſion appertayneth not to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who are profeſſed enemies to that holy Sacrament. And if ſome in <hi>England</hi> be content ſometimes to take any ſuch mattter vpon them, yet they doe it not with any obligation, or obſeruation of ſecre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, as the world knoweth.</p>
               <p>VVherefore let vs briefly ſee, what my Author declareth concerning their practiſe, &amp; doctrine in the other two points. Firſt then, he demandeth of the <hi>Hugonots,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pag. 67.</note> whether they neuer made ſhew to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree <pb n="62" facs="tcp:4752:32"/> with the
<hi>Lutherans,</hi> to the end they might the more eaſily impugne Catholicks. Secondly, he tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth them, that they would ſeeme to accommodate themſelues to the Proteſtants in <hi>England,</hi> notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding they miſlike ſo greatly their Church-go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment; their giuing of Orders, and Confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; their celebrating the Feaſts of Lord and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, of the Bleſſed Virgin his Mother, of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles and firſt Martyrs; their vſing the ſigne of the Croſſe; their ſaying the Canonicall houres; the retayning Prieſtly ornaments, and the like. Thirdly, he ſheweth, how
<hi>Theodore Beza</hi> the yeare 1556. affirmed in his <hi>Confeſsion of Faith</hi> (to draw the <hi>Lutherans</hi> to his ſect) that the body of our Sauiour was <hi>verè &amp; realiter,</hi> truly and really, <hi>in the Supper;</hi> adding that the Churches of <hi>Switzerland,</hi> and of
<hi>Geneua</hi> did belieue the ſame: and neuertheleſſe when he did ſee himſelfe contradicted, and refuſed by the <hi>Zuinglians,</hi> his anſwer was, that he ſpake not of the Lords ſupper, which is celebrated vpon earth, but of that, which ſhalbe in heauen,<note place="margin">Lib. 4. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtit c.
1. §. 2 In paruo Catechiſ. Lib. 4. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtit. c. 1. §. 4. Lib. 4. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtit. c 16. §. 24. &amp; 25. &amp;c. 1 §. 7. Lib. 3. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtit. c. 2. §. 16.17. &amp; 18.</note> where our Sauiour will be preſent
<hi>verè &amp; realiter.</hi> Fourthly <hi>Caluin</hi> in one place acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth two Churches, the one viſible and the other inuiſible. And in another place, he admitteth only the inuiſible which comprehendeth the elect. Fiftly, the ſame <hi>Caluin</hi> in one place denieth, that any man can be ſaued out of the viſible Church: &amp; in another affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, that the children of the faithfull which dy with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Baptiſme may be ſaued, although they be out of the Church. Sixtly, he willeth <hi>Anti-Coton</hi> to make theſe two propoſitions of <hi>Caluin</hi> agree: <hi>Euery faithfull man is aſſured by the certainty of faith, that he is iust, and that
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:4752:32"/> his ſinnes are forgiuen him; and that he who hath not this certainety, is not a faithfull man.</hi> And this other:<note place="margin">Ibidem.</note> 
                  <hi>No man knoweth aſſuredly, whether he hath true faith, or no: and euery man may be deceiued in this.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lib. 3. Inſt c. 13. §. 5.</note> Seauenth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the ſame
<hi>Caluin</hi> affirmeth in one place; <hi>That con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Iustification, Faith is wholy paſsiue.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In Antid. Concil. Trid. ſeſſ. 6. can. 9. &amp; 11. Lib. de ve ra reform. Eccleſ. In Antid. Concil. In conſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſ. de re Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament. In 1. Cor. cap. 11.</note> And in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother; <hi>That faith iustifieth, and is the true cauſe of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification.</hi> Eightly, in one place he ſayth; <hi>That we are neuer reconciled to God, but that togeather we receaue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herent Iustice.</hi> And in another. <hi>I maintaine</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that it is falſe, that iuſtice is either a quality, or habit, which remaineth in vs.</hi> Ninthly, the ſame <hi>Caluin</hi> in one place ſayth: <hi>that it is neceſſary for our Lords Body to be as far ſeparated from vs, as heauen is diſtant from the earth.</hi> And in another: <hi>I conclude</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that the Body of</hi> Ieſus <hi>Chriſt is giuen vnto vs really (as they ſay) in the ſupper.</hi> Where we muſt note (ſaith my Author) that he doth not only ſay, <hi>that we take the body,</hi> which he might interprete, <hi>by faith:</hi> but, <hi>that it is giuen vs,</hi> which cannot be vnderſtood, but of the preſent reali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and reall preſence.</p>
               <p>Thus much for <hi>Caluin,</hi> in whom &amp; in the reſt, which haue hitherto been ſpoken of, there is ſo much the more difficulty, becauſe all the exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples produced are in matters of fayth, in which none but heretickes hould it lawfull to equiuocate. Now my Author com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to
<hi>Anti-Coto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> &amp; chargeth him with diſſimulatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">Pag. 69.</note> becauſe vnder the colour of impugning the
<hi>Ieſuits</hi> do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine concerning Tyrants, the Secret of Confeſſion, Equiuocation, Obedience due to the Pope, or in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticuler by Religious men to Biſhops, their Generals, &amp; others Superiors, he impugneth the common beliefe <pb n="64" facs="tcp:4752:33"/> of the Church. Likewiſe, he accuſeth him of feigning at the leaſt, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> citing <hi>Silueſter, Nauar,</hi> &amp;
<hi>Eudemon-Ioannes,</hi> like a Calumniator, to make his Reader be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue, that this was the doctrine of the <hi>Ieſuits</hi> only, he hath concealed many other both ancient, &amp; modern Authors, who teach the ſame, and are alledged by the three which he nameth. Thirdly he conuinceth him of double, &amp; manifeſt malice, when in the cita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Silueſter, Accuſatio</hi> 5. <hi>quaeſt.</hi> 13. he omitteth as well in the latin in his margent, as in french in his text one of his principall reaſons contayned in theſe wordes: <hi>Quia eo caſu, cùm non ſit eius ſubditus, non tenetur dicere veritatem ad eius intentionem:</hi> Becauſe in that caſe, ſince he is not his ſubiect, he is not bound to ſay the truth according to his intention: which wordes followed immediatly after thoſe, which the calumniator alledged. Fourthly, he asketh him, whether it be not to equiuocate, diſſemble &amp; deceaue, to call himſelf a Catholike, being an <hi>Hugonot?</hi> Fifth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, he chargeth him which imputing the death of the late King to <hi>Fa. Mariana,</hi> wheras he knew himſelf in his conſcience, that this was very falſe. Which may likewiſe be ſaid of all his obiections, &amp; calumniations againſt <hi>Fa. Coton,</hi> &amp; the other Fathers of the <hi>Society.</hi> And finally, that of the ſupplicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the Queene Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent in the name of the vniuerſity of <hi>Paris,</hi> can be no leſſe, as appeareth by the decree, which I related in the beginning.</p>
               <p>In the other poynt, concerning the murthering &amp; killing of Princes,<note place="margin">Pag. 192.</note> my Author is much more large, reciting very particulerly, &amp; amply the opinions of diuers
<hi>Hugonots</hi> to that effect. But I wil only touch <pb n="65" facs="tcp:4752:33"/> briefly ſome few aſſertions of theirs.<note place="margin">Pag. 192. In appel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lat. ad No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilit. po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que Scot. Impreſſ. Geneu. Pag. 196. In Dani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el. 6. v. 22.</note> Wherefore firſt <hi>Iohn Knox</hi> openly &amp; boldly affirmeth, that the Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, Iudges, &amp; people of <hi>England</hi> ought not only to haue reſiſted, &amp; impugned Queene <hi>Mary,</hi> but alſo to haue put her to death, togeather with her Prieſtes, &amp; all thoſe who aſſiſted her, ſo ſoone as they began to ſuppreſſe the Ghoſpell of Chriſt: (that is, the Hugo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nots Religion.) And
<hi>Caluin</hi> himſelfe ſpareth not to ſay, that earthly Princes are depriued of their power, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they riſe againſt God, yea that they are vnworthy to be accompted men, &amp; that their ſubiects ought ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to ſpit in their faces, then to obey the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (all which he declareth manifeſtly to be meant of Catholick Princes.) <hi>Peter Martyr</hi> ſuppoſeth,<note place="margin">Pag. 201. In 1. Reg. c. 26. v. 12. Pag. 202. In libro cui titu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus, <hi>Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciae co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tr. Tyrannos.</hi> Pag. 215. In Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtem. di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcipl. po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liticae, li. 11. c. 28.</note> that a man may be ſure that he is impelled by Gods ſpirit to kil a Tyrant. <hi>Beza,</hi> or <hi>Stephanus Iunius Brutus</hi> giueth the people good leaue to ioyne with the Nobility, or the greater part of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, yea with any one of them, to put down a King whom they manifeſtly hould to be a Tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, euen as if God himſelfe had inuited them to vndertake that warre. And with him agreeth <hi>Bartholomaeus Kermanus</hi> auouching, That the Subiects may betake themſelues to one Noble man, when the reſt conſpire with a Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant; yea he addeth, that if there be none of the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie, who hath care of his Countrey, the Subiects may chooſe themſelues a Captaine, for the ſuppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of Tyranny.<note place="margin">Pag. 215. In politi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca cap. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>Ioannes Arthuſius</hi> ſaith in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner aſmuch, teaching that the people ought to reſiſt a Tyrant ſo long, as he impugneth the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth by wordes, deeds, ſubtilty, or craft; doing, ſpeaking, or practiſing any thing contrary to his co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant: and this in ſuch ſort, that they may depriue
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:4752:34"/> and diſpoſſeſſe ſuch a Tyrant of his office, and admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration: yea, if they cannot otherwiſe defend themſelues againſt his violence, that they may kill him, and appoint another in his place.</p>
               <p>Of the ſame opinion was <hi>VVickliffe</hi> in times paſt, as appeareth by the Councell of <hi>Conſtance</hi> which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerueth more credit,<note place="margin">Pag. 189.</note> then a thouſand
<hi>Anti-Cotons,</hi> who againſt all reaſon, would now after ſo many yeares make vs belieue, that all thoſe worthy Prelats, and learned men did eyther ſlaunder, or miſtake that wicked heretick. Neyther is the excuſe which he bringeth for him any better, ſaying; that he was not preſent in the Councell to defend himſelf: as though this had either byn neceſſary, or poſſible, <hi>Wickliff</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing dead in England 30. yeares before, and his books burnt for hereſy.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pag. 205. 206.</note>I haue reſerued
<hi>Buchanan</hi> to the laſt place, both becauſe his ſpeaches are moſt plaine, and peremp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory in this point; and alſo for that <hi>Anti-Coton</hi> ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth vpon him to excuſe him more, then any other. He therfore is not affraid to account Tyrants in the number of wolues and other hurtfull beaſtes,<note place="margin">Lib. de iure regni apud Sco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tos.</note> which whoſoeuer mantayneth, hurteth himſelfe and others: whoſoeuer murdereth, doth a benefit not only to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, but to all others in publick; &amp; if he might make a law, he would deale with them, as the Romans did with monſters, commaunding them to be carried in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to deſerts, or to be drowned in the maine ſea far from land; yea he would appoint rewardes to be giuen to thoſe, who ſhould kill them, not only by all the people in generall, but by euery one in particuler, no leſſe then to thoſe, who kill wolues and beares, or <pb n="67" facs="tcp:4752:34"/> take their whelps. And afterward he ſaith expreſly: That it is lawfull for euery one of the people to kill a Tyrant, and that this is the opinion of almoſt all na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. I omit the reſt and come to the defence, which <hi>Anti-Coton</hi> maketh for
<hi>Buchanan.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt then he excuſeth him,<note place="margin">Pag.
190.</note> becauſe he was no Deuine: But my Author ſheweth, that he endeauo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth to proue his opinion out of Scripture, which the <hi>Hugonots</hi> hold to be eaſy, and that euery one may vnderſtand it. Beſides, that there be few Miniſters eyther in <hi>Scotland,</hi> or <hi>France,</hi> better learned then <hi>Buchanan,</hi> either in diuine or humane litterature, as may in part be gathered by his Paraphraſe vpon the Pſalmes, to which
<hi>Beza</hi> (who was no ſmall foole a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them) could not come nigh. And finally the Lords of <hi>Scotland</hi> would neuer haue choſen this man to inſtruct their Prince, vnleſſe they had been perſwaded that he had byn able (according to the principles of their Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) to haue taught the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple their duty to the ſame Prince. The other excuſe, which <hi>Anti-Coton</hi> maketh, that <hi>Buchanan</hi> preſcribed no Rules in this matter, is not worth the mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; ſince that it appeareth to be moſt falſe by that little, which I haue alledged out of his large diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes to the ſame effect.</p>
               <p>This ſhall ſuffice for the <hi>Hugonots</hi> in generall: &amp; if I would endeauour to recount all the hereſies, er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, &amp; others faults conteyned in the <hi>Anti-Coton,</hi> I ſhould be to tedious. Wherfore it ſhalbe ſufficient to note ſome few particulers, which declare him to be neither a good Catholicke as he would ſeeme,<note place="margin">Pag.
249.</note> nor yet a good Subiect. As firſt, when he maketh
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:4752:35"/> a diuiſion betwixt <hi>Roman</hi> and <hi>French</hi> Catholicks, to ſow ſedition and ſchiſme, as though no good ſubiect could be a good Catholick. Secondly he ſheweth great ignorance, or rather ſome worſe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, when he cannot, or rather will not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, how God the Father loued, and appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the euent of his Sonne our Sauiours death cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the Iewes malice, which was the Redemptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our ſoules. Laſtly he calumniateth and ſlaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dereth the Pope, and Councell of
<hi>Constance,</hi> as we haue ſeene.</p>
               <p>Concerning the late King he ſheweth his little reſpect towards him, in affirming, that there was no vigour of ſpirit remayning in his time, and in making him to eſtabliſh the <hi>Society</hi> in
<hi>France</hi> for ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midity and feare; though it were againſt the good of his eſtate. And indeed all the malice, which this fellow ſheweth againſt Fa. <hi>Coton</hi> in particular, &amp; the <hi>Society</hi> in generall redoundeth to the diſgrace of the King himſelfe; ſince that he conuerſed with them ſo familiarly, loued them ſo intirely, eſteemed them ſo highly, and in al occaſions imployed them ſo willingly. Neyther doth <hi>Anti-Cotons</hi> affection ſeeme to be any better to the yong King, whome he is not afraid to ſlaunder publikly, making him ſay that which he neuer thought. And as for the Queene Regent, and the preſent Gouernment, he beareth them as little reſpect, controlling them, &amp; preſcribing lawes vnto them, diſpoſing of perſons at his pleaſure, putting away ſome, and retaining others againſt her Maieſties mind: yea calling in doubt, whether her proceedings may ſtand with <pb n="69" facs="tcp:4752:35"/> the ſafety of the preſent King her ſonnes life, or without holding her Subiects in continuall all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>armes, and defiance one of another. By this we may eaſily gheſſe, how he proceedeth with infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior perſons, reprehending the Decrees, Sentences and Iudgements of the ſoueraigne Courts, and in effect charging thoſe of the Parliament of <hi>Paris</hi> with high Treaſon; ſince that they haue freed the <hi>Ieſuits,</hi> whom this Calumniator will needs make guiltie of the late Kings death.</p>
               <p>I omit the falſification of that Courts Regiſters, as we haue ſeen. The Doctors of Sorbon haue their part alſo, being accuſed to teach doctrine different from that of the Catholicke Church, and to put vp ſuch ſupplications to the Queene, as the Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſity it ſelfe hath publickly diſclaymed. Finally this libell is ſo fraught with lyes, and ſlaunders, that many vpon ſight thereof haue proteſted, that although they had no other proofes, either diuine, or humane to diſcouer the pretended reformed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion of the <hi>Hugonots</hi> to be a pure and moſt impure hereſy, they would iudge it to be ſo by the manner of this booke, and of the like: ſince that it is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed of nothing, but calumniations, ſlanders &amp; deceipts, ſparing neither Princes, Nobility, nor Counſaile, no not ſo much as the Ladies of the Court, or Maides of Honor, though neuer ſo ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous, if they be oppoſite to them in Religion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:4752:36"/>
               <head>CERTAINE Obſeruations, and Inſtructions, for the Catholicks in <hi>France,</hi> which may ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily be applyed to thoſe in
<hi>England. §. V.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THERE remaineth now that I tell you, what aduiſes my Author giueth to his Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks in <hi>France,</hi> for the better auoiding and preuenting the danger of incurring and falling into the cunning ſleights, and hidden ſnares of the <hi>Hugonots,</hi> which he reduceth to 16. heades, and dilateth amply vpon ſome of them. I will onely, as hitherto, ſet downe the ſubſtance, as being mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to whome I write.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pag. 260. &amp; ſeq.</note>Wherefore, his firſt obſeruation is, that as her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore the <hi>Hugonots</hi> haue endeauoured to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw the ſtate vnder the ſhadow of Religion: ſo now they ſeeke to take away Religion vnder the pretext of the ſtate; as the Iewes did in the time of our Sauiour, who neglected their ſpirituall profit, not to endaunger their temporall intereſt, and by that means finally loſt both the one, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p>The ſecond obſeruation is, that the <hi>Hugonots</hi> knowing very well, that the doctrine of the <hi>Society</hi> is in all poyntes the ſame with that of the Church: haue deuiſed this plot to beguile Catholikes, by <pb n="71" facs="tcp:4752:36"/> ſeeking to make the <hi>Societyes</hi> doctrine odious, and inueighing onely againſt them; hoping by that meanes, when it ſhall appeare that the doctrine of the Church is the ſame, they may preuaile againſt that alſo.</p>
               <p>The third obſeruation is, that now in the time of the Kings minority, the <hi>Hugonots</hi> cauſe all the worſt bookes, which haue bene ſet forth for theſe 30. yeares to be printed anew, without making any mention of any anſwere giuen to them by Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes; allwaies mouing the ſame queſtions, without deſire, that the truth ſhould come to light.</p>
               <p>The fourth obſeruation is, that the <hi>Hugonots</hi> la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to perſwade the people, that the Pope hath alway been an enemy to the Crowne of <hi>France:</hi> whereas indeed the <hi>French</hi> Kinges are preferred be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore others in the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> being called the eldeſt ſonnes of the Church, and their Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour taketh place before others. By the name of King abſolutly, without addition, is meant the King of
<hi>France.</hi> The Popes graunted for a time a priuiledg to theſe Kings to confirme their election: they haue giuen Indulgences to ſuch, as pray for them: they haue exempted them from the excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication of any Biſhop of their Realme, &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted them to receaue the B. Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vnder both kinds the day of their conſecration, and when they prepare themſelues to dye, for their <hi>Viaticum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The fifth obſeruatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is, that the <hi>Hugonots</hi> vſe fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſly to affirme that the Popes take to themſelues power and authority to change &amp; diſpoſe of Kingdomes at <pb n="72" facs="tcp:4752:37"/> their fancie &amp; pleaſure, which is moſt falſe.</p>
               <p>The ſixt, that the <hi>Hugonots</hi> would perſwade the world, that ſome Catholikes are <hi>Roman,</hi> &amp; ſome
<hi>Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all,</hi> whereas all good Catholiks are both; the one in reſpect of their Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; the other in regard of their affection to the State. And experience hath allwaies ſhewed, that thoſe who are moſt reſpectiue to the Church, are likewiſe moſt aſſured to their Prince.</p>
               <p>The ſeauenth, that the <hi>Hugonots</hi> giue out, that thoſe who defend the Popes Authority, retaine ſtill ſome old leauen of the league; which are moſt dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous ſpeaches, contrary to former decrees, &amp; ſufficient to renew old ſoares: not vnlike to that other Calu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niation, by which the ſame <hi>Hugonots</hi> vſe to apply that which the auncient Fathers, &amp; the Scripture it ſelfe hath ſpoken of
<hi>Rome</hi> while it was Pagan, vnder the perſecution of <hi>Nero</hi> &amp; his ſucceſſors, to the ſame Cittie as it is Chriſtian, and to the Sea Apoſtolik, with intent to make the Pope &amp; Cardinalls odious or contemptible.</p>
               <p>The eight, the <hi>Hugonots</hi> to curry fauour with Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates, the Doctors of <hi>Sorbo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> the Curates &amp; other Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall men, and to incite them againſt the <hi>Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety,</hi> make a ſhew of praiſing them; telling ſome, that the <hi>Society</hi> doth not loue them, nor yield them obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience; and others, that the Fathers contemne them, ſpeake ill of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; will ſwallow vp the Vniuerſity, if they be let alone. Wheras the <hi>Society</hi> is ſo farre fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> being ſeparated from the Clergie and the Prelates of <hi>France,</hi> that they are beloued, and maintained by al, and ſpecially by the fiue Cardinalls, &amp; nyne Arch-Biſhops which my Author nameth; and allmoſt by <pb n="73" facs="tcp:4752:37"/> all the Biſhops without exception; yelding vnto them all due obedience, ſubmiſſion, and fidelity. But theſe deuiſes of ſowing diſcord is noe new matter in the Church of God, as my Author ſheweth by many ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples</p>
               <p>The nynth, when any Catholike ſetteth forth a booke impugning hereſy, the heretikes ſeeke preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to diſcredit the Author by al ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner of inuentions. And to diuert the Reader, they ſpread abroad many little libels, ſonets, anagrams, and ſuch other toyes. Thirdly, when this will not ſerue, inſteed of anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, &amp; defending themſelues; they goe on in repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting their old obiections and arguments, as though nothing had been ſaid vnto them; adding only ſome new calumniations after the manner of all former he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retikes.</p>
               <p>The tenth, they carp at euery word and ſillable, where they can eſpy the leaſt aduantage in any Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Authors writing; and of this we haue a nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble example in a booke lately publiſhed by <hi>F. Coton</hi> himſelf; in which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mending the Kings of <hi>France,</hi> &amp; ſhewing their rare priuiledges, he vſeth theſe words: <hi>Our Kings in France;</hi> where preſently the <hi>Hugonots</hi> took hould of that particle
<hi>in,</hi> &amp; would make the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pler ſort belieue, tha <hi>Fa. Coton</hi> had only affirmed, that their Kings had thoſe priuiledges in
<hi>France</hi> it ſelf; wheras it is euident, that thoſe wordes <hi>(in France)</hi> haue not refere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to the priuiledges, but to the Kings themſelues. And beſides my Author ſheweth, that he could not ſpeak properly in any other ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner, becauſe to ſay <hi>(our Kings of France)</hi> is noe very good French: &amp; if he had only ſayd <hi>(our Kinges)</hi> it had beene to ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, <pb n="74" facs="tcp:4752:38"/> and might haue been wreſted by a malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Aduerſarie to other Kings, aſwell as to thoſe of
<hi>France.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The eleuenth; the ſame carping humor, which they vſe in miſinterpreting and wreſting to a contrary ſenſe the writings of Catholickes, they practice no leſſe in calumniating their actions. As for example; wheras <hi>Fa. Coton</hi> was beloued by the late King: they ſay that he had bewitched him. He was his Confeſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius: that is, in their interpretation, a flatterer. He was his Preacher: that is, he praiſed him. The King heard him willingly ſo many yeares: that is (ſay they) he kept others backe. He eſteemed his ſpirit, wiſdome and eloquence: that is (in their opinion) <hi>F. Coton</hi> ſpake ill of all, and murmured againſt others. The King would haue him with him at his meales, in his Coach, and when he went to walke: this they inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prete, that the Father intruded himſelfe euery where. The King did willingly ſee his writings, &amp; read ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times a Manuall of Praiers, which he dedicated to the Queene: this (ſay they) was to flatter God, and to bring him a ſleepe with wordes that ſauour of his quean. The King tooke pleaſure in his diſcourſes, &amp; propoſed to him diuers queſtions: out of which they inferre, that the Father was a man of incredible impude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy. The King did willingly ſee him at al times, and in all places, as well after ſo many yeares, as in the beginning; which they call, to be tyed to the Kings girdle, &amp; to aſſiege his ſpirit. The King deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him nothing, that he demaunded: the cauſe wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of (in their iudgment) was, becauſe he would take no denyall. The King was very beneficiall to the
<hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety,</hi> 
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:4752:38"/> aſwell in reſpect of the affection, which he bare to the whole Order in generall, as in regard of Fa.
<hi>Coton</hi> in particuler: which they would haue to be by reaſon of <hi>F. Cotons</hi> extorſion and importunity. The King founded them Colledges, and gaue them meanes to liue: for which cauſe they compare the <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety</hi> to a Canker, which alway gaineth ground. The K. permitteth them to haue a Nouitiate in the Suburbs of S. <hi>Germain:</hi> by which they vnderſtand an inclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure wherin a Citty may ſtand. The <hi>Society</hi> haue more Schollers then others haue: the cauſe therof (ſay they) is, for that they take nothing for waſhing and candles. Their Sermons are frequented with great concourſe: becauſe (in their interpretation) they ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the people, and preach ſedition. Many goe to them for the reſolution of their doubts, or to confeſſe their ſinnes: the reaſon of this (ſay they) is becauſe they get whole inheritances into their hands. They are beloued of the Princes: which theſe men calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niate, ſaying, that <hi>Fa. Coton</hi> maketh himſelfe their fellow. They are mantained by the Nobility, Parla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, &amp; other Magiſtrats of <hi>France:</hi> for which cauſe the <hi>Hugonots</hi> ſay, that they haue their Schollers, and diſciples in all places. They are ſent by God to repreſſe hereſie: theſe men anſwere, that
<hi>France</hi> was Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke before the <hi>Ieſuits</hi> were in the world (they ſay not, that <hi>France</hi> was not ſo infected with hereſie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore themſelues.) They are learned, and ſkilfull in all languages, and ſciences: for this cauſe in the iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſome (that is of the ignorant or malicious) they will deſtroy learning. They are vertuous, and for all that the heretiks haue raiſed, inuented, and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:4752:39"/> againſt them, they could neuer prooue any thing hitherto: and therfore are inforced to ſay, that they diſſemble, and to call them hypocrites. Finally they eſteeme that which is white, blacke; that which is ſweet, ſower; and that which is good and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable in the opinion of others, is naught and dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable in theirs.</p>
               <p>The twelueth deceipt which the <hi>Hugonots</hi> vſe is, to call thoſe ſeditious which anſwere them, and to calumniate ſuch, as maintaine the accuſed; terrify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their friends, and reprehending them, as though they were the occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of all the inconuenie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, which come by ſeditious writings. And in this many Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiks are much miſled being vnacquainted with the humor of hereticks, who like to their Maiſter the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, vſe to fawn and yeeld to thoſe who are at de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiance with them, and reſiſt them manfully: but aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſault thoſe fiercely, whom they ſee moderate, or fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. Which was the cauſe, that the ancient Fathers <hi>S. Iuſtin, Tertullian S. Athanaſius, S. Chryſoſtome, S. Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome, S. Tho. of Aquin,</hi> &amp; <hi>S. Bonauenture</hi> wrote ſo many learned and earneſt Apologies in the defence of Chriſtian Religion, and Religious orders. And ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it is very ſtrange, that any ſhould thinke much at the anſwers of the innocent party, hauing beene pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoked by ſo many falſe calu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>niations and bitter inue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiues. Of which we need go no further for an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, then to that, which paſſed in <hi>Paris,</hi> before
<hi>F. Coton</hi> wrote his Declaratorie Epiſtle.</p>
               <p>The thirteenth is, that ſo ſoone as any Miniſter hath ſet forth a booke fraught with lyes, deceipts, &amp; ſlanders: it ſerueth for many other to write vpon the <pb n="77" facs="tcp:4752:39"/> ſame ſubiect, with any little alteration or addition. And of this my Author produceth many exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples both of former times, &amp; at this preſent. For after the
<hi>Anti-Coton,</hi> came out diuers other Pamphlets here in <hi>Paris</hi> to the ſame purpoſe, which my Author briefly exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth in 5. or 6. leaues. But I find nothing worth the mentioning, except I ſhould tell you, that they raile bitterly againſt a certaine Gentleman called <hi>Monſieur de Courbouzen Montgomery</hi> a man of great valour, wiſdome, &amp; deſert, who hath lately forſake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonots</hi> after long diſputations with them, inſomuch that none of them dare encou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ter with him any more. But he glorieth &amp; eſteemeth it a great honour to be thus abuſed, and hated by Gods enymies.</p>
               <p>The fourteenth obſeruation, which my Author maketh, is that the ſinnes &amp; tranſgreſſions of the <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonots</hi> ought not to be ſo little eſteemed among Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes; ſo that when they eate fleſh in Lent, laugh at the holy Sacrifice of Maſſe, raile at the Pope, break Images, or teare pictures, burne Reliques, taking the Reliquaries to themſelues, and commit ſuch other a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſes incide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to their deformed Religion, many make light of it, &amp; in a manner think it lawfull for them to doe theſe thinges, becauſe they are <hi>Hugonots;</hi> wheras the truth is, that an Heretike ſinneth more in comit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting theſe things, then if he were a Catholike. Which appeareth plainly in the ſin of Rebellion &amp; Treaſon, where he who not only reuolteth againſt his King but maintayneth alſo that his Rebellio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is iuſt, ſeking to draw others after him, &amp; teaching that all thoſe are in euill eſtate who will not ioyne with him in that wicked action, committeth a far greater offence, then <pb n="78" facs="tcp:4752:40"/> another, who falleth into the ſame cryme, but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgeth his fault, accuſeth himſelf from tyme to tyme, ſeeketh not to perſwade any, and finally doth nothing, but of meere frailtie.</p>
               <p>The fifteenth deuiſe of the <hi>Hugonots</hi> is, to charge thoſe who defend the <hi>Ieſuits</hi> of being addicted to the
<hi>Spaniard.</hi> For which cauſe my Author taketh vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him to examine the ground of this deceiptfull obiection. Wherfore (ſaith he) if this proceedeth from being <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits;</hi> the Societie began in <hi>France,</hi> in the Colledge of <hi>S. Barbara,</hi> which is in the Vniuerſitie of
<hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris.</hi> Yf it be in reſpect of their being Religious men, euery man ſeeth, that there are many other beſides them. Yf in reſpect of
<hi>France,</hi> they in that Countrey are French-men, and there is no reaſon, why a French-man, ſhould not loue his nation, as well as any
<hi>Spaniard</hi> doth his, or as well, as the <hi>Portugheſe, German, Italian, Engliſh,</hi> thoſe of <hi>Iapo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia</hi> and <hi>Perù</hi> doe theirs. Yf in regard of the three Religious vowes, they are common to all Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous orders, euen to the Knights of <hi>Malta.</hi> Yf in reſpect of the fourth, which is peculiar to them; that belongeth leſſe to the
<hi>Spaniards,</hi> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>podes:</hi> for it concerneth only their miſſions among Infidells, and the conuerſion of other loſt Soules. Yf this imputation be laid vpon their Rules; they are commanded by one of them expreſſely to loue, and reſpect all Nations in our Lord, alway giuing the chief place euery man to his owne, as the rule of well-ordered charity doth require. If their fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions be obiected, theſe are as profitable, &amp; more neceſſary in <hi>France,</hi> then in
<hi>Spayne:</hi> neyther can any <pb n="79" facs="tcp:4752:40"/> of them be attributed rather to <hi>Spayne,</hi> then to any other Nation: beſides that many other principall perſons do preach, teach, and confeſſe, who not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding are not accompted <hi>Spaniards.</hi> Yf the reaſon be, for that the
<hi>Society</hi> hath one Generall: the <hi>Carthuſians,</hi> and the
<hi>Dominicans</hi> haue but one during his life in like manner. Yf becauſe he is not a Frenchman, thoſe of other Orders are no Fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men neyther. Yf becauſe he is a Neapolitan, ſonne to the Duke of <hi>Atri,</hi> and great Vncle to the Duke who now is: he is not therefore a <hi>Spaniard.</hi> Yea his moſt noble houſe hath been alwaies allied to thoſe of <hi>France,</hi> witneſſe the Counteſſe of <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteau-Vilain</hi> his Neece. Yf they obiect, that hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>Society</hi> hath had Spaniſh Generalls: ſince the time of B. <hi>F. Ignatius,</hi> who was the firſt, and of <hi>Nauar;</hi> there haue been but fower, two <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards,</hi> Fa.
<hi>Laynes,</hi> and Fa. <hi>Borgia,</hi> who before had beene Duke of
<hi>Gandia;</hi> the third Fa. <hi>Euerard Mercurian</hi> who was borne in Liege; &amp; Fa. <hi>Claudius Aquauiua</hi> who now liueth, and is an Italian, as hath beene ſaid. But ſuppoſing, that they had all beene
<hi>Spaniardes,</hi> that they were ſo ſtill, and ſhould be ſoe hereafter: were this any greater cauſe for Frenchmen to complayne of the
<hi>Society,</hi> then <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards, Italians,</hi> and other Nations haue to be grieued, that there be three Generalls of diuers Orders in one only Prouince of <hi>France.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But perhaps they will ſay, that the King of <hi>Spayne</hi> is a great benefactor of the <hi>Society:</hi> notwithſtanding the truth is, that neither this King, nor his Father, nor any of his Predeceſſours, Kinges of <hi>Spayne</hi> did <pb n="80" facs="tcp:4752:41"/> euer found one Colledge for the <hi>Society.</hi> And if any will ſuſpect, that at leaſt he alloweth ſome penſions; the contrary is manifeſt. For ſince that the
<hi>Society</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſeth any recompenſe for their labours and functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; it can much leſſe admit any penſion. And noe man aliue is able to proue, that euer any French Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther receyued a penny from the King of <hi>Spayne.</hi> Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, no man can deny, but that the late King <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> the fourth fauoured the <hi>Society</hi> exceedingly, beſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed great benefits vpon them, had great confidence in them, and obliged them in all reſpects to loue him: ſo that it is hard to ſay, whether of the two calumnia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions chiefly contayned, and inculcated in the <hi>Anti-Coton,</hi> be greater; That the
<hi>Society</hi> teacheth any do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine different from that of the Catholicke Church: or, That they ſhould haue any hand in the late Kings death.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, my Author ſheweth, that there is noe cauſe, why
<hi>Spaniards</hi> ſhould be ſo odious to <hi>French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> ſince that they are good Chriſtians and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks, aſwell as other Nations, and there is now no warre, but peace betwixt theſe two nations, ſending their mutuall Embaſſadors one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, calling one another brethren, their Subiects hauing free traffique among the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues. And if this hatred ariſeth from any thing that is paſt, there want not the like occaſions with others, who not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding are not thus inueighed againſt, nor ought to be, although they differ alſo in Religion. Wherefore this can proceed from no other ground but from the malice of the Diuell himſelfe, who is the Father of all diuiſion, and ſeeth very well, that <pb n="81" facs="tcp:4752:41"/> the good and quiet of the Catholike Church depe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in great part of the vnion betwixt theſe two puiſſant Nations.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <head>A BRIEFE Relation of <hi>F. Cotons,</hi> and the
<hi>Societies</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings; togeather with a Chalenge to the
<hi>Hugonots,</hi> and a Supplication to the Queene Regent. <hi>§. VI.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FOr concluſion of this whole diſcourſe, I haue reſerued theſe three points, which my Author handleth vpon different occaſions, and in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers places. Firſt then, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning <hi>Fa. Coton,</hi> he ſaith that he is a Chriſtian, a Catholike, a Prieſt, a Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious man, who goeth to Confeſſion, and hath cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated the holy Sacrifice of the Maſſe euery day for theſe eighteene yeares, he hath beene of the <hi>Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> 27. yeares and more, in which he hath ſtudied Rhetoricke, Philoſophy, Diuinity, the languages, &amp; Mathematiks: and ſince he hath alſo taught Huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, Rhetorick, and moral Diuinity, and preached in many of the moſt principall Cittyes of the Realm: He hath often diſputed both by word and writing with diuers Miniſters, and other <hi>Hugonots.</hi> He hath aſſiſted in the conuerſion of many, eſpecially in three Prouinces, and that in great number; and ſince his being at the Court, he hath laboured in the reduction of the Earles <hi>de Lauall, de Caſtelnau, de Mainuille, de
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:4752:42"/> Vaſſan, de Chaumont,</hi> and many other: he was ſent for thither by the late King, when he thought no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing leſſe, being at that time in <hi>Auignion:</hi> his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation, his learning and his manner of life were ſo agreeable, and pleaſing to his Maieſty, and his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, that he did not onely retayne him at the Court, and in his retinue: but alſo made him his Preacher, and afterward his ordinary Confeſſarius. His ſermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, diſcourſes and proceedings were ſo farre from being tedious to the late King, that he deſired to haue him alwaies in his ſight and company, in ſo much that he made choice of him to heare the generall Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of his whole life; and did alwaies vpon euery occaſion prayſe, honour, &amp; commend him, defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding him againſt all his aduerſaries. The whole Court will teſtifie, that nothing was euer obſerued in his manners, or doctrine, which might offend or ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalize any.</p>
               <p>When he was healed &amp; recouered of the blow, or ſtab, which was giuen him, it pleaſed his Maieſty to ſay vnto him: <hi>You had neuer a better blow, for the world hath diſcouered the loue which I beare you, and I haue ſeen what affection the world beareth you.</hi> And another time vpon another occaſion he ſaid: <hi>Fa. Coton ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth well of all the world, he is neuer heard to ſpeake ill of any.</hi> Moreouer <hi>Fa. Coton</hi> is knowen to haue refuſed Biſhopricks, &amp; Arch-Biſhopricks, for which cauſe his Ma<hi rend="sup">tie</hi> told him once, that if he were Pope, he would oblige him to accept of them. But the Father decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnto him, how this was repugna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to the Inſtitute of the <hi>Societie,</hi> and to the particular vowes, which he himſelf had made, and that nothing had done more <pb n="83" facs="tcp:4752:42"/> harme to Religious Orders, then the deſire to haue of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, or Benefices. Which anſwere pleaſed his Ma<hi rend="sup">tie</hi> ſo much, that he reapeated it often, &amp; before diuers. And this is that which confoundeth the detractors of the
<hi>Societie,</hi> when they are demaunded <hi>Cui bono,</hi> ſhould theſe Fathers be ſo wicked &amp; vnnaturall? For, if they doe it for pleaſure, they might enioy it more free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, more lawfully, &amp; in farre greater aboundance in the world, remayning in their commodious, &amp; many times noble houſes, which they leaue to enter into Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. If it be for profit, there is not any Colledg in <hi>France,</hi> which is able to ſpend twentie poundes a man, as hath been ſaid. And if any will endeauour to proue the contrary, he ſhall haue the ouerplus for his labour. If they doe it for honours: they renounce them all by a particular vow, by which they are bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d vnder mortall ſinne not to admit, or receaue any dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, but by force &amp; conſtraint, being commaunded by him, who hath authoritie to doe it.</p>
               <p>What therfore can remayn, why they ſhould aba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don father, mother, kinsfolks, countrey, goods, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, dignities, hopes, yea &amp; their life it ſelf, which they expoſe not only amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g Infidels, &amp; barbarous na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, but (which I eſteeme more painfull) among heretiks, and bad Catholikes, with whom they muſt continually encounter &amp; combat? Which in reſpect of the Catholiks is very ſtrange, ſince that they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not deny, but that the Fathers teach the youth paſſing well both in manners &amp; learning. 2. They preach the word of God with ſatiſfaction, and contentment of all Nations in Europ. 3. They carry it to the <hi>Antipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des</hi> in
<hi>Aſia, Africa, America,</hi> to both Eaſt &amp; Weſt
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:4752:43"/> 
                  <hi>Indies.</hi> 4. They defend it againſt heretikes with conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall danger of their liues in <hi>England, Scotland, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople,</hi> and in all other places, where their aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance may be a comfort to afflicted Catholikes. 5. They heare Confeſſions, adminiſtring that Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t exactly. 6. They viſit the ſick. 7. They help the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that dye. 8. They goe to the Priſons. 9. They teach the Catechiſme, or Chriſtian doctrine. 10. They intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the frequentation of Sacraments. 11. They ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther preach, confeſſe, teach, nor exhort, but by the conſent of the Biſhop in the dioceſſe where they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide. 12. When they are incorporated into any Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitie, as they are at <hi>Tholoſe, Bordeaux, Reims, Caën, Bourges, Cahors, Poictiers,</hi> they obſerue the lawes of the ſaid Vniuerſities, acknowledging the Rectors, &amp; performing exactly whatſoeuer is ordayned. 13. They haue among them many men of rare qualities, and the greateſt part very well borne. 14. They haue at this preſent 30000. ſchollers, and in time paſt haue had more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> two hundred thouſand in their Claſſes, whome they haue taught, &amp; do teach to feare &amp; ſerue God, and aboue all to keep themſelues from mortall ſynne, by the meanes of often confeſſing, &amp; freque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t receauing, binding them all without exception to doe this euery moneth. 15. And among all this great number of ſchollers, there hath not one been fond to haue complained of any leaſt word ſpoken vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which might tend to any immodeſtie, but they will all teſtifie, that one of the cheifeſt cares which the <hi>Societie</hi> hath, is to preſerue them in Angelicall puritie &amp; integritie, ſo much as may be. 16. One of their <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety</hi> through extreme frailty &amp; exceeding great tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptation, <pb n="85" facs="tcp:4752:43"/> became a Miniſter among the
<hi>Hugonots</hi> in <hi>France:</hi> of whom there hath been inquiry made, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the liues of the <hi>Ieſuits</hi> be wicked &amp; impure, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they haue intelligence, &amp; correſpondence with forraine Nations, whether they be hypocrites, and in a word, whether they be ſuch, as the
<hi>Anti-Coto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> hath ſince deſcribed them? To all which he anſwered, No; and that all is falſe. 17. Their life is not monaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call nor ſecret, they liue and conuerſe with all men, they are ſeen euery day preaching, confeſſing, diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and diſcourſing. Now then who euer heard the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſweare, braule, blaſpheme, detract, ſpeak wantonly induce to euill, or ſeduce any? If this Calumniator hath reported any ſuch thing, where are his proofes? 18. Their books in all manner of ſciences, &amp; in al la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages are to be ſeen in all places, and are eſteemed by all ſuch as haue not the reformed ſpirit of contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction. 19. Kings &amp; Princes vſe them for the guiding of their ſoules. 20. The Popes haue approued their Inſtitute, &amp; the Councell of <hi>Trent</hi> hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmed it. What can be ſaid to theſe proofes? Are they conie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures, ſuſpicions, or raſh iudgments? Is it neceſſary to beg the penne of Miniſters, to make a demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? Oh how far is this age from the conditions of true charitie, which are, 1. neither to think, 2. nor to iudg, 3. nor to ſpeake, 4. nor to liſten to euill of any; 5. but to interrupt ſuch talke; 6. or if this ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be, to excuſe the action. 7. If not this, at leaſt the intention: 8. or attribute it to paſſiion: 9. &amp; if there be no other excuſe, at leaſt exaggerate the tentation: 10. and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies ſay, that if God did not help vs, we ſhould doe worſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="86" facs="tcp:4752:44"/>By this which hath bene ſaid, it appeareth what reaſon my Author hath to tell the <hi>Hugonots,</hi> that they ſhould do more wiſely to deſiſt from theſe calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niations againſt the
<hi>Societie,</hi> eſpecially among Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes, to whom by this meanes they diſcouer the irreligion of their Religion, and make them ſee that their pretence is not to conſerue the flocke of Chriſt, but to diſcredit their Doctors, impoſe ſilence to their Preachers, and depriue the youth of their good, &amp; faithfull Inſtructors. They perceaue well inough, that the quarell is not only with <hi>Ieſuits,</hi> though they be the capitall enemies of their deformation; but their mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning is to ſet vpon all Religious Orders, &amp; the whole Clergy, and hauing preuailed againſt ſome, they will vndertake the reſidue, as they did at <hi>Antwerp.</hi> But to aſſault them altogether were to painfull, hard, and impoſſible a matter. Wherfore they would deuide, &amp; weaken them, and ſo cut of one after another; as <hi>Themiſtocles</hi> diſcomfited the Army of
<hi>Artaxerxes,</hi> conteining aboue a million of Souldiers, intercepting them troupe by troupe in the ſtrait of <hi>Helleſpont.</hi> Or as their brethren did in <hi>England,</hi> drawing to their par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty at the beginning the Biſhops and ſecular Clergy, vnder pretence that Religious men belonged not to the Hierarchie of the Church; and that Chriſtianity was before them; and that the ſplendour of theſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular Orders ſeemed to obſcure the dignity of Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drall Churches, and diuert the people from their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes &amp;c. And by theſe fraudulent deuiſes the Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byes being thus put downe, and the Monks turned out, and ſome of them alſo put to death for deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Kings Supremacy; the aforeſaid brethren <pb n="87" facs="tcp:4752:44"/> informed the Nobility, that the great riches, which the Church enioyed, were giuen by their Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors; and that there could no better courſe be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in this great diſorder of the Popedome, and in this licentious and voluptuous prodigality of the Biſhops, then to reduce all thinges to their begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and to render theſe Eccleſiaſticall goodes to the houſes, out of which they firſt came. And in this manner <hi>Scotland</hi> was depriued of Religious me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Prieſts, Curates, Chanons, Abbots, &amp; Biſhops: which alſo had been brought to paſſe in <hi>England,</hi> if the <hi>Puritans</hi> might haue preuailed: The ſpirit of their M. <hi>Caluin</hi> being impatient of all Superioritie, and Eccleſiaſticall Hierarchie.</p>
               <p>Moreouer my Author telleth the <hi>Hugonots,</hi> that by their perſecutions they eſtabliſh the <hi>Societie</hi> more &amp; more: for they are eſteemed ſo much the more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable, as by them they are deſcribed vnprofitable; &amp; ſo much the more neceſſary, as they account them harmfull. And the like is of others, who are no here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks; for euery man obſerueth, that thoſe who perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute the <hi>Societie,</hi> are neither the deuouteſt, nor the beſt Catholiks of the world; which might eaſily ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, if they be Churchmen, by inquiring whether they ſay their Breuiarie or not; and if they be lay, by marking, whether they frequent the Sacraments, not to ſay any more.</p>
               <p>To all which we may add, that the <hi>Hugonots</hi> haue been heard ſay in their moſt ſecret Conuenticles, that if they ouerthrow not the <hi>Ieſuits,</hi> the <hi>Ieſuits</hi> will o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrow them; that is, their pretended Religion; which is the cauſe, that they ſet vpon the
<hi>Society</hi> more <pb n="88" facs="tcp:4752:45"/> fiercely, then vpon ſome others, on whom notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding they might probably take as great hold. For my Author ſaith, that he cannot belieue, that they are more zealous of the State, then of their Religion; and therfore there muſt needs be ſome
<hi>enigma,</hi> equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocation, and myſticall vnderſtanding in this great, fierce, and terrible perſecution, which they haue reſolued in their night-aſſemblees againſt the <hi>Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</hi> But he biddeth them do their worſt, which will be the beſt for them, ſince that they are men, who haue nothing either to looſe, or gaine in this world, but only the ſeruice of God, and the ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſoules.</p>
               <p>Wherefore they, who will haue, and vſe them in this ſort, may; and they who will not, may ſend them to <hi>China,</hi> and
<hi>Mogor,</hi> where the harueſt is plentifull. And if nothing els did hold them in <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope,</hi> but pleaſure or profit, they would long ſince haue departed of their owne accord: for they are not ſo kindely dealt withall, that they haue any great cauſe to pleaſe themſelues according to ſenſe; but their contentments, yea (I may ſay) their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights are croſſes, tribulations, ſlaunders, perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions, and eſpecially, when they come from <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti-Cotons,</hi> and their aſſociats, enemies of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick faith. They are neuer more content, then in ſuch diſcontentments; neuer more ſtrong, then when they are thus weakened: neuer more vnited to God, then when they are caſt of, and ſeparated from this kind of people. All their affliction conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth in the offence committed by their enemies againſt God; in the harme, which Catholicks re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue;
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:4752:45"/> &amp; in the loſſe of the <hi>Hugonots</hi> ſoules: Soules, for which they would expoſe their bodyes, &amp; liues a thouſand times.</p>
               <p>Notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding they make no great accompt, nor haue any great apprehenſion of the <hi>Hugonots</hi> attempts: they know, what they can do, of what weight and value they are: it is all but threats and menaces, which they vſe moſt, when they trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for feare. <hi>Caluins</hi> ſpirit is inſolent in proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, deicted in aduerſity; and of it aboue all the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits in the world, we may truly ſay: that he threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth who is much afraid. They know alſo, that it is proper to God, to defend and maintaine that, which the Diuell impugneth, as they haue experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enced by their returne into <hi>France.</hi> For in exchange of 9. or 10. yeares of abſence from that part of the Countrey which belonged to the Parliament of <hi>Paris,</hi> they haue ſince, not only been reeſtabliſhed there, but alſo eſtabliſhed in the whole Kingdome, with more augmentation and increaſe, then their continuall ſtay could haue produced in an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeares. So true it is, that God recompenſeth with vſury, whatſoeuer is done or ſuffered for his ſake.</p>
               <p>Wherfore they haue reaſon not only to hope, but alſo to be certainely perſwaded, that vnleſſe God ſhould retire himſelfe from
<hi>France</hi> for their ſinnes,<note place="margin">Pag. 302.</note> the
<hi>Society</hi> ſhal hereafter be imployed and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed in this Kingdome more then it hath byn hitherto: and that in regard of this ſtorme, after which (as is to be hoped) will ſhortly ſucceed a quiet calme; eſpecially vnder the gouernement of <pb n="90" facs="tcp:4752:46"/> ſo wiſe a Queene, whome God hath choſen like an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other <hi>Debora,</hi> during the minority of this Great and Little King her Sonne, and their Maiſter, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſhadow of her Royall protection, the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious men of this <hi>Society</hi> ſo much enuyed by the wicked, and perſecuted by thoſe who know it not, will alwaies breath the ſame aire of deuotion to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God, and of inuiolable fidelity towards their Maieſties: requiring one only grace for all the hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſeruices, which they deſire to yeild them; and it is, that when they ſhalbe accuſed in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon, or in particuler, either in manners, or doctrine; it will pleaſe them to ordaine, that moſt exact inquiſition be made, to chaſtice them, if they be culpable; or to puniſh the accuſers, if they be found inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent.</p>
               <p>And becauſe the Author, or Authors of the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti-Coton</hi> are obliged both voluntarily by their own word, and neceſſarily by the qualitie of the cryme of calumniation to tell, and declare their names &amp; qualities; they beſeech her Maieſtie, that it will pleaſe her to commaund, that if within 8. daies they doe not manifeſt themſelues, all the rigors and penalties, which Gods and mans law preſcribeth and inioyneth againſt Calumniators, may be vſed againſt them: and that ſhe would appoint to this end, that extraordinary ſearch, and inquiry may be made. And in caſe, that they freely name and diſcouer themſelues, my Author in the name of all the Fathers, and particulerly of Fa. <hi>Coton,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrateth himſelfe at her Maieſties feet, beſeeching her by all the extenſion of graces, and power <pb n="91" facs="tcp:4752:46"/> which God hath giuen her, to accord, that Iuſtice may be done aſwell of Fa. <hi>Coton,</hi> as of all the reſt, if the Calu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>niators ſhall verify, &amp; make good that which they haue ſaid; and of them reciprocally, if for want of proof, they ſhall be found conuinced of impoſture, or ſlaunder. And he telleth her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, that this is a matter of no ſmall importance, and therefore ſhe will be pleaſed, not to attribute this their humble requeſt to importunity. For it belongeth to the ſeruice of God, who hath inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt in their functions, if they be ſuch, as they are deſcribed. The good of her Maieſties people doth alſo require the ſame: for they ought not allway to liue in this heſitation, but muſt be cleared from the ſiniſter impreſſions, which they may haue concea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by reading theſe infamous lybells.</p>
               <p>The reputation likewiſe of the late King, her Maieſtyes deare ſpouſe, the great <hi>Henry,</hi> their Lord and good Maiſter, is engaged herein; which is ſtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with the calumniations, that are impoſed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, whome his Maieſtie did not onely chooſe, loue, and fauour; but honour alſo with the office of his Preacher, and ordinary Confeſſarius. Likewiſe her Maieſty her ſelfe hath part herein, ſince that ſhe imployeth Fa. <hi>Coton</hi> in the ſame charges and offices about her ſonne, which he exerciſed for his Father. The honour of the Lords of the Counſell is touched alſo, ſince that they ought to repreſent vnto her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty the euills and daungers, which enſue by the <hi>Societyes</hi> ſtay in <hi>France,</hi> if they be ſuch, as they are accuſed to be.</p>
               <p>Finally it importeth Fa. <hi>Coton</hi> much, who cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:4752:47"/> hath not deſerued to be handled in this ſort, Innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie is the ſiſter of truth: truth is ſyrnamed the daughter of God, and God himſelfe is called the God of truth, by whoſe loue my Author beſeecheth her Maieſty, that ſhe will cauſe the truth to appeare, that it may deliuer them: &amp; they will beſeech him ſo much the more, that he will be pleaſed to increaſe his gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in her Maieſty, to make her Regency peaceable, the wils of her Subiects vnited, and the Scepter of the King her Sonne happy, and of long continuance.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <head>The Concluſion.</head>
               <p>THVS I haue run ouer the whole anſwere to the
<hi>Anti-Coton.</hi> And though I haue omitted many things of good importance, yet I feare, leaſt in ſome I may ſeem to haue been too tedious, eſpecially writing to you (my Reuerend &amp; deareſt Fathers) to whom I may iuſtly ſuppoſe, that neither theſe Calumniations of your
<hi>Societie,</hi> nor the ſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons or anſwers can be ſtrang or new. But I hope you will pardon my prolixitie, &amp; accept of my good will: and hereafter in like occaſions, I ſhall learne to be more warie. For which cauſe I will omit all other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, though this Cittie of <hi>Paris</hi> be no leſſe fertile in this kind, then <hi>London</hi> it ſelfe. For I ſuppoſe you know long ere this, how the Treatiſe of Cardinal Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine,
<hi>De poteſtate Su<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mi Pontificis in temporalibus, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſus Gulielmu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Barclaiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> was prohibited by this Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lament of <hi>Paris</hi> the 26. day of Nouember laſt paſt, &amp; that this Decree of theirs was recalled foure daies af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <pb n="93" facs="tcp:4752:47"/> by the King himſelf in his Counſell, aſſiſted by the Queene Regent his Mother, the Prince of <hi>Conde,</hi> &amp; Earle of <hi>Soiſſons,</hi> Princes of the bloud, the Duke of
<hi>Maienne,</hi> the Lord Chancellor, the duke of <hi>Eſpernon,</hi> of
<hi>Lauardin,</hi> &amp; <hi>Boisdaulphin</hi> Mareſhall of <hi>France,</hi> Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miral, &amp; great Maiſter of the horſe in <hi>France,</hi> giuing large Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſion for the Executio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of this his Decree &amp; reuocation to al Baylifs, Sherifes, Prouoſts, &amp; Iudges, their Leiutenants, and other his Maieſties Iuſtices &amp; Officers to whom it might appertayne, as appeareth by the Decree it ſelf, &amp; the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſion dated in <hi>Paris</hi> the laſt day of Nouember, in the yeare 1610. and of his Maieſties Raigne the firſt.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="signature">
                           <p>
                              <hi>By the King in his Counſell.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>Signed
<hi>Delomenie.</hi>
                              </signed>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>And with this I will humbly take my leaue, wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing you all happineſſe, and deſiring ſomtime to be partaker of your holy Sacrifices and Praiers. And ſo I euer reſt</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your Fatherhoods moſt aſſuredly to commaund. <hi>F. G.</hi>
                  </signed> 
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>From Paris</hi>
                     <date>
                        <hi>this</hi> 20. <hi>of February</hi>
1611.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:4752:48"/>
            <head>THE CONTENTS OF the aforeſaid Letter.</head>
            <list>
               <item>§. I. Concerning the Doctrine of the <hi>Society</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugned by the <hi>Anti-Coton.</hi> pag. <hi>12.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>§. II. The Solutions to the perſonall obiections against the Fathers of the <hi>Society.</hi> pag. <hi>22.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>§. III. The Solutions of the obiections againſt
<hi>Fa. Coton</hi> in particuler. pag. <hi>50.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>§. IIII. A briefe note of the doctrine, and proceedings of <hi>Anti-Coton</hi> and other <hi>Hugonots.</hi> pag. <hi>61.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>§. V. Certaine Obſeruations, and Inſtructions, for the Catholicks in <hi>France,</hi> which may eaſily be appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to thoſe in
<hi>England.</hi> pag. <hi>70.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>§. VI. A Briefe Relation of <hi>Fa. Cotons,</hi> and the
<hi>Societies</hi> proceedings; togeather with a Chalenge to the
<hi>Hugonots,</hi> and a Supplication to the Queene Regent. pag.
<hi>81.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:4752:48"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
